Hey, guys.
I'm thrilled to be
joined today by Nick Joseph,...
...the head of pre-training at Anthropic.
To give viewers a high-level
sense of what we'll be covering, we're
...with the basics
of what pre-training is, and then dig into
...about strategy, data, alignment,
and infrastructure at Anthropic.
And by the end,
you'll hopefully have a sense for how
...in AI comes directly
from advances in pre-training.
I would love to talk a
little bit about your backstory...
...and kind of how you got to this point.
Where did you work before Anthropic
and what were your takeaways from those
Yeah.
So, let's see, I was at Vicarious, uh,
and then at OpenAI, uh, before Anthropic.
So, Vicarious was originally an AGI lab,
and sort of when I joined, they were sort
...making a shift to product,
particularly working on robotics products.
And the thing I worked on was,
like, training, uh,...
...computer vision models for,
for their robotics products.
It was my first job,
so I think I just, like, learned a ton how
...machine learning models, how to,
like, write machine learning
And at the time,
were you also thinking about a career as
Like, at the time,
a lot of people doing AI work were in
That's kinda what I was thinking
about before I started to do a company.
Like, how were you thinking about
that in your headspace?
Yeah. So, like, I mean,
actually we went a little bit...
I think, like, a lot of my thinking
on this had come from an internship I
...at GiveWell, which is,
like, a nonprofit that evaluates
And some people there being like,
"Ah, well, at some point we might have
It could be dangerous.
We should worry about these risks.
This could be, like,
a big impact on humanity." Yeah.
And I was, like, not
super convinced at the time, and went down
...and was gonna try to work on,
like, directly helping people in poverty.
That didn't work out for various reasons,
and ended up...
...being, like, "Okay,
I'll at least work on AI.
Either, like, the safety thing
will turn out to be important and I'll on
...won't be and I'll just
make cool things with AI that can probably
...poverty more." I wasn't really
coming at it from an academic standpoint.
I was sort of like...In fact, when I switched to that, it was
Part of the appeal was that I could,
like, immediately go do stuff in AI.
Whereas if I wanted to work in,
like, economic policy, I'd have to wait, I
...know, six years, do
a PhD- Totally....and then start, and,
Ah, it's a, it's a longer path.
And, and what did the
state of AI safety work at that time even
Like, who are the people
who were thinking about that kind of
I mean, there was some folks
at Vicarious thinking about this kind...
...of thing, but it was
fundamentally a robotics company.
And, and so yeah, how,
how were you thinking about that at the
Yeah, so my sense was,
like, at the time, a lot of the...
...AI safety discussion
was kind of theoretical.
Like, the models
weren't actually that good.
Right.
They weren't really posing these dangers.
So it was a lot more, like, philosophical.
It was like, "Oh, at some point
we might get AI that's really smart,
...than humans, and, like,
should we weight this, like, future Right.
"How should we compare
that to near-term things?" And I think
...like, actually a, a,
just a less compelling argument. Yeah,
I think it was, like,
an interesting one and, like, sort of made
So, next you went to OpenAI.
What was OpenAI like at this time?
Yeah. So, I was at OpenAI.
I was on one of the safety teams and kind
Uh, I ended working
on code models, actually.
Okay, cool. Nice.
And kind of when I got there I could...
The first thing I saw was, oh,
they had fine-tuned GPT-3 to write some
Okay.
And it was really good. Okay.
And I was like, "Oh, okay." Cool.
"If you're worried about AI getting really
...writing its own code,
that seems-" Yeah, totally. "...seems like
...Yeah, totally. "And how,
how likely is that to happen?" So, it was
...a bunch of evaluations and,
like, studies of what contributed.
Yeah.
And then after, like, uh,
eight months, uh, basically everyone I...
...worked with, like all,
all the safety leads left. Cool.
Which, uh, yeah,
invited me to go to Anthropic and that
...sort of the reason I joined OpenAI,
was because I cared...
...about AI safety
and wanted to work with them. Totally.
So, then I went,
went with them to join Anthropic,...
...uh, pretty much right when it started.
With that, why don't we transition a bit?
These days you run the
pre-training team specifically at
Um, obviously you've been working on
pre-training at Anthropic for quite a bit
...I'm sure it's evolved over the years,
what that even entails and looks like.
Why don't we start by just talking
a little bit about what pre- pre-training
Like, how does it even fit into
the way of thinking about how AI models
...developed at a place like Anthropic,
and what exactly do you guys do?
We know that one of the
ingredients to making AI models better is
You want to put a lot of compute in.
And if you sort of
step back and you're like, "Okay, what's
...could put the most compute into a,
into a model possible?" We need...
...some objective that there's just,
like, tons of data for.
And one idea here is, like, the internet.
The internet is massive.
It's probably the biggest, like,
single source of data humanity has
And you don't have labels.
It's like you, you don't
want someone to have to go in and look,...
...read the entire internet and,
like, say something about it.
So, you want to get
labels out of the data itself.
Yeah.
And the idea here is we can take some text
and we can predict the next word.
So, you take, you know,
"the" as the first word, you predict the
...word, then you say,
"the cat", you predict the word after
And this means you get very dense signal.
Every, every word is like a new example,
and there's a huge amount of data.
And one of the findings from my GPT-1,
GPT-2 was kind of as you...
...throw more compute at this,
more data, bigger models, uh, you...
...get better and you,
you get smarter models, essentially.
Totally.
Um, and that's kind of been the
central thesis of pre-training for the
Mm-hmm.
Uh, there's this idea of scaling laws,
which is that you can...
...actually quantify, like,
as you put in more compute, more,...
...more data, more parameters,
you get models in a very...
Uh, you get a lower loss of...
A better prediction of the next
word in a very predictable way. And I
You can somewhat foresee from
that original paper,...
...and I think,
like, Dario did foresee this.
I think many people did.
But what wasn't obvious was
that once you have that, there's...
...this positive feedback loop
where you can train a model.
You can use it to make something useful
and sell that and get more money.
Yup.
Use that to buy more compute.
And then you just
actually train a better model.
Yup.
And I...
We've sort of run
that cycle- Yeah....over and...
...over again over
the past five years or so.
Well, in thinking about
that objective to begin, you know, I
The way I think about
the state of pre-training is, yeah, it
...like this next word prediction,
at least from the external standpoint,...
...seems to be the
dominant way pre-training happens.
But if I rewind the clock
to that era of 2017 to 2020 or 2021 and
...was all sorts of pre-training
objectives people were considering, right?
There was these, uh,
BERT and BART models that were doing mass
It seems like this
GPT series of models doing, uh, modeling
...describing, this next word prediction,
seems to be the dominant one that won out.
Do you have any reflections on
that time period?
Like, were you guys trying all of them
and kind of this one worked?
Or, or is there some sort
of first principles reason why...
...this is, like,
the right one that should have worked?
I think the answer is,
like, it's mostly imperial.
Like, in terms of how
to think about these things, I'd be like,
Just try them all, see what works.
One big advantage for
this autoregressive setup is that you can
...generate text afterwards in a fairly,
like, straightforward way that comes...
Yeah.
It's- Like, enables
a product use very nicely. Yeah.
Um, like, one thing that you want is,
like, just one characteristic you want...
...from a setup is, like,
a loss, whereas you drive down the loss.
That actually is the thing you care about.
And you can think of it as, like,
if you got to perfect on language...
...modeling, you now can,
like-...write text as a human.
You can sort of imagine,
you put in the title of a paper and it...
...should spit out the entire,
uh, spit out a novel paper.
Okay.
Whereas I think some of the other
approaches don't quite have that, uh,
Yeah, totally.
Yeah, and- and it makes sense
that in terms of that loop you're of,
...know, then release something
that gets you revenue and you can use that
...more compute and iterate,
this sort of gives you the most natural
...actually do that flow
because you can keep releasing new and
...getting the revenue from
that to invest in more compute and so on.
Yeah, it certainly gives
you the most open-ended thing.
You can imagine, you know,
you, like, train something as a classic...
Like, you- you train some base thing,
you fine-tune...
...it for a bunch of particular tasks.
One approach people would use,
they would, like, do this big
...and then they wouldn't just,
like, open-endedly sample from it.
You'd fine-tune it on,
like, a hundred specific tasks.
And th- that could work too.
I- I think that, like,
the one sort of general intuition I...
...have is, like,
compute is the thing that matters. Yeah.
So, like, I think if you throw
enough compute at any of these
...you're gonna get something
that's probably pretty good- Yeah.
...uh, and can kind of
be fine-tuned to other things.
And it's- it's surprising
how little these details matter...
...compared to throwing
more compute at the problem.
When you think about actually
throwing more compute at the problem, a...
...whole bunch of axes by
which you could throw compute at it too,
In...
If you have a specific model
architecture you're training over, you...
...can basically throw more data at
that specific architecture.
For a particular one,
you could add more layers or make the in
You could do some kind of neural
architecture search over lots of different
And I assume that these days it,
it's somewhat more figured...
...out, you know,
which architecture you go for.
I assume the earlier
days it was somewhat less so.
And, and I'm curious
if you could speak to how you guys thought
Like, what did your infrastructure
even look like to do that type of
I mean, I think the a- the
short answer is it's hard, right? Yeah.
Like, what you're really
doing is you're gonna train this one...
...big expensive model
and you have a space of, you know...
You can sort of call these
things hyperparameters, you know.
How many layers do you have?
What's your width?
Like, you have a space
of hundreds of hyperparameters...
...and you want them all to be optimal.
Yeah.
And you're sort of
striking this balance actually...
...between how much do they matter. Yeah.
Like, can you just take your best guess
and throw more...
...compute at it-
Yeah....in whatever way you want?
Yeah, and this thing
basically doesn't matter, right?
At some point- Versus how
much you wanna get it precisely correct.
Yeah, interesting.
And I think one of the,
like, interesting things is,...
...like, it actually
doesn't matter that much.
Like, we...Like, I think this
was in one of the early scaling loss
Like, you can change these things
and get little wins, but, like, as...
...you throw more compute,
it- it sort of reliably gets better.
If you mess up enough, you will,
you will sort of stop seeing that
...Yeah....and you won't have
any way to know, which is one of the...
That's, like, kind of the
hardest part in some ways, but it's-...
...You don't know
the counterfactual basically, because you
...run it for long
enough to actually know what it is.
Yeah. We have these scaling laws.
So you, you can sort of say, like,
as you train a model with more and...
...more compute,
you expect the loss to go down as a power
Yeah.
It's really a power
law plus constant. Yeah.
So what eventually will
happen is you'll curve off that power
...Right, right....and
then you know something is wrong.
And is it fundamental?
Is it, like, you've hit the limits of
Nope.
Or is it, nope, you should have changed,
you should have tweaked...
...your learning rate
slightly differently? Right, right.
And that's- that's
sort of one of the challenges.
In terms of how to,
like, figure it out, you can...
The- the usual paradigm is,
like, test things out at small...
...scale- Yeah....before
running them at large scale.
Mm-hmm.
And try to find things-
Small scale in terms of data or in terms
Uh, in terms of everything. Oh.
Like, you kind of
want to scale things down, like,
So you want to say...
Like, you want, you want
to have some theory for, like, how you're
Like, "Ah, okay,
if I get 10 times as many flops-...
...Yeah....how much
of it goes into layers?
How much of it goes into data?
How much of it goes into attention?"
And you sort of get that theory
and then test that it's optimal a...
...bunch with, like,
scaling everything down proportionally.
And- and just so I can think
about what this actually looks like-
in those, in those
early days of Anthropic, you know, you're
...of, like, 10
or something like that in those very early
Or 12, maybe.
What actually is your ability
to use large scale infrastructure...
...as, like, a relatively
nimble startup at that time?
I mean, a startup
that was well-capitalized, but...
...still not actually
that many people working at.
What kind of infrastructure
did you have access...
...to, to train these
early models at the time?
So that was actually
one of the wild things, was that at
I mean, you don't know
what anyone else is doing, of course-
but it kind of felt like we were,
like, at the frontier- Yeah....
of it and there just weren't
that many people who cared.
Yeah.
Like, I was sort of coming, you know...
I was coming at it from,
like, "We're making AGI.
This is the most
important technology ever." Yeah.
And then we'd kind of,
like, look around and be like, "And it...
...seems like I'm one of 30
people who-" Right "...who are working...
...on this-" Right.
"...in, like, the world." Yeah.
I mean, I was kind of,
like, junior person.
Everyone else sort of knew how to do this
and had done it...
...before, but I was kind
of surprised at how easy it was.
Oh. Oh.
Um, like the public
estimates for GP3 I remember were...
...that it cost five
million dollars to train.
Yeah, yeah.
Which you're like, on the one hand,
five million's kind of a lot-...
...Yeah....but it's, like,
a lot for an individual person. Yeah.
It's not really a
lot from, like- Yeah, totally....uh, a
Like, a startup
or whatever. Yeah, totally.
So w- we could totally buy,
like- Yeah....compute...
...that was enough
to train models like that.
Yeah.
You could- And were
you using a cloud provider or-...
...or did you have
a custom setup somewhere?
Or what...Did you literally
have racks in a room somewhere that you
You know, bought a bunch of NVIDIA GPUs
and you were doing it?
Uh, we were using a cloud provider,
but I think it's kind of...
It's not actually that different-
Yeah....because one of the things that's-
...to me is you actually have
to understand the- the literal layout.
Like, uh, I remember at one point, uh,
one of my coworkers running a clustering
...Okay....to identify what rooms all
of the chips were in since we- we had a
...Huh....that they were
in different rooms and that was causing,
Or, you know, different
building- Some sort of network latency
Some sort of network latency. Okay.
And you can kind of figure it out.
You can, like, reverse engineer.
Like, "Ah, okay, yeah-" Interesting .
"...there's clearly, like, two...
...clusters here that are connected
better." Very interesting. "And there's...
...some issue on the
connection between them." Like, you're...
We're trying to push the
limits of- of the hardware, like, as much
Um, particularly at the beginning
when we were kind of...
...like, "We have way
less funding than everyone else.
We have to..." And-
and most people weren't very efficient the
So we were like, "Ah,
we can get a big lead by being really at-
...we use the compute." Could you
talk a little bit about some of the things
...did in those early days
for how to get the most out of the
I think that's really interesting.
Like, I think back to the days of...
The early days of Google, for example,
where there's these e- there's...
...these cases where they
basically bought relatively cheap consumer
...and then they optimized
the software to make it so you can get...
...the most bang for your buck out of them
and that's how they had all...
...this high latency or low latency,
high availability stuff.
I'm kind of curious
if there's some analog in the early AI era
I think for us,
it was largely about, like,...
...getting the distributed
framework right. Mm-hmm.
So, like, we're training on...
In order to train these models,
you have to train them on a large number
Yeah.
And there's a bunch of
different approaches to- to how to do
There's, like, data parallels
and there's pipelining.
Yeah.
There's upsharding.
And, like, getting all of
the- And at the time, there were no, like,
...source packages you could just grab
and use that just worked for this.
I mean, today, there's
somewhat more of these.
But at the time,
I assume there was literally none.
There were some.
Like, I actually remember
that we were working on all kinds...
...of data parallels
to them- Yeah....early on.
And it was like,
"And now we write the, all reduce it." And
...was like- Right...."We
really do this ourselves?
We don't, like,
call a package?" It's like...
Right.
And this was kind of like,
"Well, we're gonna want to modify it,"
Like, "Oh." Like, "We don't want
to outsource this to some package because
...we're about to go
to a bigger scale." Like, it's PyTorch,
They had a package for doing this.
Totally. Totally.
But we were gonna go to a
bigger scale than Facebook had been to .
Right. Right.
And you don't want to
have a dependency on a package, uh, that
...gonna have to be, like,
constantly modifying, essentially.
It's a, it's such a
counterintuitive sentence there too.
Like, "We're going to a
bigger scale than Facebook was," because
...Research was considered one of
the best places to do machine learning
Like, FAIR was one of the pla-...
FAIR and DeepMind were
hiring lots of people out of...
...top PhD programs
and doing lots of things.
Like, what was your head
space when you were like, "Okay, this,...
...this very established
lab with great people and whatnot, we...
...are operating on a scale
that is not relevant to them"?
Like, was that natural
and obvious to you or was there times
...kind of doubted the
decisions you were making in that
I think it was surprising.
I will...Maybe I'm just too arrogant or
Yeah. Yeah.
I kind of looked around and was like,
"What are these people doing?
They're all missing the,
like, big picture here." Yeah.
Like, I, I think the
scaling laws were pretty clear.
Like, the, and the arguments against it,
I just thought were kind of nonsensical.
Like, you know, you,
the scaling, I think the original
...laws paper had,
like, 11 orders of magnitude.
Yeah, yeah.
And there was, like,
this intense debate on whether it...
...would continue for,
like- Right....another point.
Right.
And I was like,
"Hap-" 'Cause it was already 11.
It seems, it seems like one over
11 is maybe your chance it, it fails here.
And then, like,
you know, sometimes it doesn't work.
Like, sometimes it
just works straightforward.
Yeah.
You're like, "We'll just
train the model." You're like, "Oh...
...yeah, of course." But yeah,
I do think that it was...
It maybe felt obvious when
you're in that head space, and you're
...on this all the time,
and you're making- Yeah....those plots.
And I think these
things feel pretty different when you're
You know, there's a huge space of papers.
Everyone tries to make their paper sound,
like, very robust and, and important.
Totally. Totally.
I, I could see,
I could see it being like, "Oh,...
...yeah, this is
not really a thing." Right.
Totally.
But also, diff- labs
have different cultures.
Yeah.
So, like, I think one
of the things at FAIR was it was...
...a very more PhD-style,
independent research.
Hmm. Mm-hmm.
People have their own ideas, pursue those.
You're fighting for
your compute and so on.
Yeah. Yeah.
And to do a project,
like training a large language model...
...requires a lot of
people to collaborate- Yeah.
Yeah....on, like,
a really complicated piece of
...Yeah, totally....that
isn't going to be a paper, right?
Totally.
Like, you're, you're not gonna publish,
like, "Oh, I got a slightly...
I got 5% more efficiency
-" Yeah, totally .
Totally. "...than the next one." Yeah.
Um, and it's not respected in,
like, those cultures necessarily.
Yeah. Interesting.
So, that might've been part of it.
Okay.
So then, when
you actually implement these, these you're
...using a level
of low-level programming where, you know,
...like PyTorch, but you're perhaps
not using everything right out of the
...from PyTorch, 'cause there's
things you guys want to customize that
...at the level of basically
one level of abstraction below them.
But not necessarily at the
level of abstraction of, you know,...
...writing custom CUDA kernels or,
or, like, was that also in, in...
...the space where you
guys were thinking about things?
So, it depends on,
like, the operations. Yeah.
So, like, I think I was
mostly operating at the level of, like,
Yeah, yeah.
You know, like, uh, yes,
where does the MATMUL go?
Yeah.
But not thinking, like,
"How do you make the MATMUL efficient?"
Like, I assume Torch
figured out how to make a...
...MATMUL as efficient
as is possible. Totally.
But there are some pieces, like attention,
where there was...
...just kind of a lot
of different- Yeah....variants.
And attention is really complicated
and hard to make efficient...
...on- Yes....a GPU and the,
those things you have to kind...
...of go, go more levels
down- Yeah....um, the stack.
Uh, I think there was, like,
a process that is maybe interesting that
...like, thought of before of,
like, how to do it, which is sort of, out
...problem, the thing you're going to do,
coming up with a strategy for how to
...it, that, like,
can get to- Hmm....a really good Hmm.
You know, like, uh- So, like,
you're thinking about MFU basically,
...your, your utilization-
Yeah....on your GPU? Yeah. Yeah.
So, there's, like,
a goal utilization you're trying to get...
...at and a strategy
to get to there, you're saying?
Yeah.
And I think, like, one of the
things you can do is you can actually, and
...map out what efficiency-
Hmm....you're going to be able to get to,
You know all the constraints.
It's- Yeah. MFU and, and is FLOPS
Yeah.
But, like, the reason you don't
get good MFU is you end up limited on HBM
Yeah.
You end up limited on, I don't know,
as re- host, like, CPU offload. Yeah.
There's a bunch of different pieces.
Yeah.
But it, but there's not that many pieces.
Right.
There's, like, six relevant- There's,
like, six, yeah , yeah....numbers there.
Totally.
So, you can totally model it
out- Yeah....understand what the
...are- Yeah....and
then implement something that can get
It, of course, will be really inefficient
when you implement it. Yeah.
And then the next step is,
like, pulling out a profiler.
So, you wanna be able to profile
the job- Yeah....look at how long every
...takes- Yeah....have a model
in your mind of how long every
...should take- Yeah....and
then make those, the two things the same.
Yeah.
And, and were there good
out-of-the-box profilers you...
...could use at that time
or did you guys have...
You know, because people weren't
operating on the kind of network
...you guys may have been using,
did you have to write your own
...basically, to do this type of,
you know, multi-node optimization?
Yeah. It depends when.
Yeah.
I mean, they were
actually getting better with time.
The PyTorch profiler was,
like, pretty good- Yeah....
actually, throughout
for a single GPU. Mm-hmm.
If you wanted to profile a GPU,
the PyTorch profiler would work.
But if you wanted to profile
a job on- Yeah....hundreds, thousands...
...of GPUs, that, like,
hadn't really been done much. Yeah.
And then that was kind of more of us,
like, hacking into the- Yeah....
profiler to figure out
how to combine all the traces together.
And then one more
question on that earlier is, you know, you
...you know, you hadn't really
done a lot of this work before maybe...
...some time at OpenAI and,
and those early days in Anthropic.
How did you actually
go learn all this stuff?
Like, what was your process
for learning about those six things...
...that were relevant to
bandwidth limitations and whatnot?
I mean, so when I
joined Anthropic, one really...
...nice thing was
there just wasn't that much.
I think my first day,
I read through our entire, uh- Right .
Like school....all, all of Slack. Uh-huh .
And the entire, like, internal database.
And learned a bunch from that.
Yeah.
Like, it was kind
of nice to just be like,...
..."Everything is
relevant to me." Yeah, totally.
And then I mostly
learned from pair programming.
Like, uh, Tom Brown
had done all this before, so he...
...kind of, like,
knew all the stuff quite well.
Sam McCandlish,
my manager had also done a lot of it
And I just, like, paired with them,
uh, a huge amount at the beginning.
And I think one of the things
I really like about pairing as a way of...
...learning is you learn the,
like, thing you're trying to do.
Yeah.
Like, you, you will learn that.
Like, if you're pairing
with someone better than you, they...
...can just do it,
so you're mostly just watching them.
But you also learn how people do it.
Hmm.
So, something like a pro- how to use
a profiler is not something you would ever
...from seeing- Right....someone's,
like, final write-up on Slack- Right .
Right.
For their PR.
You would just be like,
"Oh, they found these-" Right. "...they
...this specific line." Right.
"It's a win." And they, they- Yeah.
Like, you-did you watch, like,
a YouTube video for four hours of
messing around with the profiler to,
like, maybe self-teach it or something,...
...or to actually pair with
someone is basically the best you can do.
Yeah.
I think there was, like,
one thing that I- I think is embarrassing
...look back is I'd never
actually used a debugger before- Mm-hmm.
Yeah....joining Anthropic.
People talk about it, PDB.
I'm like, "Yeah, yeah,
that's a thing people use," but print fine
Yeah sure, sure.
And then I, like,
watched someone and was like- Sounds about
..."Oh, no, a debugger
is a super useful tool." Yeah.
This person's way faster
at debugging things. Yeah, totally.
Particularly if it
takes a long time to start...
...up the code, which- Totally....it can.
And, yeah, lear- learning
that sort of thing, I think, comes best
Yeah, totally.
Uh, and then there's, of course,
the obvious, you just learn by doing.
You know?
Yeah, totally.
I eventually did, like,
spin a profile and stare at it for many,
Totally , exactly, yeah.
Okay, so, so then tho- that was sort of
Over time, obviously
pre-training has become bigger and bigger.
As you're describing scaling,
I imagine you're using...
...many X more GPUs,
much more compute over time.
I'd be really curious to
hear first at a high level, what do you
...changed about the pre-training strategy
that you could talk about?
Obviously, there's more compute,
but what does that actually mean to have
...terms of what you think about
differently from those early days versus
I'm sure there are things
that haven't changed- Yeah....'cause I...
...think it is, like,
shocking how- Okay, yeah, that's really...
...interesting, yeah....little
things change in some ways.
Like- Yeah....
I think I'm still pushing
down the exact same metric-...
...Okay....that I was on, like, day one.
Yeah.
Like- There's some
loss function...Loss go down.
Yeah, cool.
And I think you could,
like, look at some of...
Like, you could probably run
the origin- the first model I trained...
...on the same
metric and just- Yeah....like, make a plot
...like, progressive team- Nice,
nice....over, over time.
Yeah, totally.
Uh, so that's all the same.
I think the biggest- Yeah,
like one OKR is, like one...
...thing that matters basically,
yeah, totally. Yeah.
And, like, I don't know,
I mean, talking about, like, OKR, it's...
...very size of the company,
like, oh, should you do OKRs?
Sure, sure.
And it's always felt a
little bit funny for- Yeah....uh, a team,
...where I'm like, "Sure,
I can just pick a loss value." Right,
But, like, the answer is, like,
as low as possible.
Yeah.
We will continue to work on that forever.
I think the biggest things
that have changed has been a little more
Like, I think at the beginning...
I mean, the first,
like, three or six months, I...
...tried to read
every PR in the code base.
And that was great. Sounds familiar .
I knew all the pieces-
Yeah....et cetera.
And as you grow, it's,
kind of, everything gets,...
...like, a little more precise, you know?
Yeah.
People really dial in exactly
how attention should work, let's say.
Or, you know, really dial in,
like, uh, the parallelism strategy.
Yeah.
And, uh, you end up with a team
where it's a bunch of people who...
...are, like, deep
experts on- Yeah....individual things.
Which is great,
because it means you can go, you can go...
...really deep on those things,
but sometimes you, uh...
A- at least for me as a manager,
one of the things- Yeah....you sometimes
...to think about is, like,
making sure the bigger picture makes
Yeah, totally.
And also that you have enough people
who actually do understand- Yeah....the...
...whole bigger picture that there's no,
like, single point of failure.
Yeah, it- it's interesting you-
you frame it in that, with that trade-off,
Because as- as you were describing that,
I was trying...
...to think, you know,
is this a bug or a feature?
Like, there's some obvious features of it,
which is you...
...get expertise
and you can optimize certain things.
But I imagine your ability to
take bigger swings becomes more
...if not everyone's
exactly pointed in the same direction.
Like, how do you wrestle with that now?
Yeah, I think I mostly just
try to get a balance- Yeah....uh, of
I think one of the
challenges early on- Oh, people?
Oh, that's interesting.
Yeah, like, I think people
really do have a preference here. Yeah.
It's been one of the
things I've seen. Yeah, yeah.
Like, there are people
who really want to be a generalist-
and understand everything and,
like, lightly touch on things.
Sure.
There are people who wanna,
like, pick an area.
Often, they've already picked
that area- Yeah....
and they're, like,
deep experts in precision.
Yeah.
You know, they studied,
they did a whole PhD in precision...
...and just- Yeah....want
to think about that.
Yeah.
And you want to get some balance of that.
I think earl- there was a phase
where we'd hired a lot of people who...
...are more generalist shaped-
Yeah....'cause that's what the people...
...who joined- Yeah,
totally....early started for the .
And then you ended up with,
kind of, everyone doing everything- Yeah.
...and no one really,
really deeply understanding one thing.
Yeah.
Uh, and that's one failure mode.
But I think if you get
too many people who are specialists, you
...a lot of effort has to come
from the manager- Yeah....from, like,
...lead to connect everything-
Yeah....and to notice something like,...
...ah, if we change the architecture here,
that would make this, like,...
...efficiency consideration-
Right....over there way easier.
Right, interesting, yeah.
Um, one of the things I really liked,
kind of, like, at the very beginning was,
...I was working on efficiency,
but I could just go and, like, be like,
...what if we change the way we do,
like, this particular step?" Yeah.
And people would be like,
"Oh, yeah, that's probably...
...fine." Like- Totally....easy change.
And then, like,
you could avoid this whole complicated
...to make this operation
that was hard efficient- Yeah....
because you can make
an easier operation efficient.
Mm, very interesting, yeah.
So, as the level of
compute has also gotten bigger, so I'm-
...imagine, okay,
there's more GPUs now, you have to network
Are there some, like,
kind of non-obvious challenges that have
...time where you guys have just,
like, banged your head against the wall
...solve them because of the
amount of computers you're dealing with
...people would otherwise know about that,
like, you want to share?
I think that connecting
them is one that's maybe interesting...
...and, like- Oh,
interesting....surprisingly hard.
Okay. 'Cause you really do get more
and more chips connected and...Yeah.
Like, one thing that I think is,
like, the- the standard way people
...chips- Yeah....isn't, um,
the whole thing is one failure to made.
Like, one chip fails- Mm....the whole thing can crash.
Mm.
And- The standard way
as in the standard way people doing AI or
...other fields where
people are doing- Uh, in AI for ?...
I mean, at least, like,
I think at the beginning, you know?
Yeah, sure. Yeah.
Like, first- first
versions of things- Yeah, totally....were-
...this way and-
So it's like you have 100 GPU cluster or
...is 128, like,
if one of them dies, job fails basically.
Yeah, I mean, the simplest
thing is if you just, like, distribute
Yeah.
So say you put, like,
every layer on a different- Ah, yeah,...
...okay, cool....uh,
chip and you lose, like, layer seven.
Yeah.
Like, yeah, you're not gonna,
like- Model stops, yeah, exactly....skip
Yeah , totally.
I guess you could. Yeah.
But that's, like,
a pretty weird model training process now.
Yeah, totally.
And, like, that leads
to some interesting things which is
...okay, so now as you scale up,
you have more and more chips...
...and the failure rate
can get like larger and larger.
On the other hand,
you can, like, I don't know,...
...you can, like, restart pretty quickly.
There- there's nothing that
you- you have to, like, load back in some
Yeah, totally. Yeah.
So that was one thing.
And then I think it was,
like, the level of novelty at the...
...whole stack is
something that's surprising. Mm.
Like, basically everything from,
like, how the chips are laid out in the
...center- Mm....to the
chips themselves- Mm....is pretty new.
Yeah.
There- there just haven't been
that many generations- Yeah....of GPUs.
Yeah, interesting.
I think one of the things that...
I don't know, when
I learned computer science, my code
...work and I'd be like,
"Oh, the computer's broken." Yeah.
I think my teacher was more like,
"You can trust the computer's...
...not broken, but you-
you messed up." Yeah, interesting.
Yeah, it's- it's you messed up.
And I think one of the most
frustrating things I encountered in AI
...was working on
something and being like, "I don't know
...wrong, I'm just totally stumped." And,
uh, my manager looked at it and...
...it was like, "Uh, yeah,
probably the computer's wrong." Oh.
And I was like, "That
seems unlikely." And sure enough, the was
Oh, interesting, yeah.
Turned out that, like,
the GPU was broken and- Huh,...
...yeah....uh, we
had to-...pull in a new one.
But you have to, like, think, like...
Having to think about that,
like- Yeah....the...
...GPU could be wrong,
the GPU could be slow.
Yeah, totally, totally.
Like, these sorts of issues.
Uh, the power supply in the data center be
Totally.
There's so m- so much more,
like, level of depth- Mm-hmm....
than you, like,
kind of expect to need as a- Yeah....
Python programmer.
And, and just to visualize it,
like, in those early days, I assume...
...you guys were using the number of GPUs,
it's probably on the...
...order of tens to hundreds
or something like that per run.
It's probably not tens of thousands
or hundreds of thousands per run, or...
...what was the rough size
you guys were at in those very early days?
Yeah, let's see.
On the order of thousands?
I think they were, like- Like,
could they fit in this room?...yeah.
Yeah, thousands.
So, like, you could
have a bunch of racks and...
...you could fit them into,
like, one room.
I assume these days it's
basically like a building for, for one of
Yeah, now I think it's,
like, you know, huge, huge campuses.
At the time, it was,
like, kind of unclear.
It was like, "Oh, I think..." Like,
we were like, you know, "Do we need...
...them all in one room?" Yeah.
"Can we be spread across multiple
...Like, uh, and, you know,
you, we had these theoretical models.
We were like, "Oh, we need this much
bandwidth from point A to point B." Right,
But you're like...
You never know how far down
you have to go, like- Yeah. "Oh, but like,
...do we need?" Like,
what if there's like a single capacitor
...all of them and we, like,
turn on the whole job at once. Yeah,
Like, does that crash things?
Totally, yeah.
And so do you have to think about
differences in the different types of
I mean, you guys work with
all sorts of different cloud providers.
From your standpoint,
are these just sources of compute?
Or if you guys are using TPU versus GPU,
are these, like, you know,...
...Google TPU versus NVIDIA GPU,
do you actually have to think as an...
...engineer differently
about what it means to train on these two?
Yeah, so I
mean, fundamentally they're all, they're
Yeah.
They're all computing the same- Yeah,
by some tensor operations.
...forms of matrix
multiplications, et cetera.
The way they do it is pretty different,
and the way that...
...you program them
is- Yeah....is pretty different.
Uh, and then also the actual specs,
uh, end up pretty different.
You know, some, some might have,
like, a lot of flops and not very much
...they might have a
lot of memory bandwidth, but not very much
So I think a lot of...Ha- having multiple chips is, like, great
It means you can actually, like,
take the job and put it on the chip that
...works best on, and that's- But,
like, are there certain types of jobs
...would work better on, like,
a TPU cluster versus an NVIDIA GPU
Like, how would you- Oh, yeah, for sure....uh, think about that? Oh, interesting.
Could you talk about that? Yeah.
Yeah, I think, like, one example is,
like, inferences of workload in
...Yeah, okay, makes
sense....tends to require more HBM
You, you end up doing- Yeah....you,
sort of the simplest...
...form of sampling since-
Yeah....you're going one at a...
...time, you have to load
all the weights for every token.
Yeah.
And that means you
might want a lot of HBM bandwidth.
Uh, pre-training actually
is often more flops intensive because...
...you, you have a lar-
larger batch sizes essentially.
Yeah.
Um, so yeah, so you,
you can sort of specialize...
...which chips you use for which purposes.
The downside of having
multiple chips is that...
...you have to write
the thing multiple times.
Right.
Uh, you, in theory you could
have abstractions across them, but
...Yeah....they're different enough
that it's pretty hard to do that.
So you can sort of end up,
if you do all the workloads on all the you
...multiplying your work-
Yep....work by the number of chips you
Yeah, on your, on your point about
sometimes the computer just breaks, I
...remember you giving me an anecdote of,
uh, my company at the time was doing...
...something with Google TPUs and
I was telling you something, some anecdote
...how we were having
some esoteric seg fault error and you were
...me something to the effect of like,
"You should have used them six months...
...ago before we help them fix
like half of the problems they had on
...TPUs." And so I can
imagine how you guys deal with a lot of...
Especially with these very new chips,
like lots of problems that arise that...
...you guys kind of like
work closely with the providers to fix.
Yeah, the partners are,
like, pretty great about fixing things.
Yeah, totally.
I think it's, like, interesting to
figure out the right way to do that form
...because- Yeah....like,
they have a strong incentive to fix them,
Like they, they want,
they want the chips- Yeah....to work for
They, they want to- Totally....sell us more chips in the future.
We obviously have a very
strong incentive for the chips to work.
Totally.
Because we like buy them long in advance,
you know, like...
...everything's riding
on getting these clusters to work.
Totally.
Um, but we don't have, like,
necessarily totally share, you know,...
...like all information
sort of can't be shared across.
So yeah, one of the,
like one strategy that's managed is...
...like making these
sort of small scale reproducers.
So like when you get a problem,
you know, like usually what we're doing is
...training some giant run
and we get like a seg fault from USA and
...okay." Like, "Hi, you know,
we got a seg fault on your cluster." And
..."I don't know how to fix that."
So you have to kind of be able to like it
...of your code base and be
able to like reproduce the issue but on a
...chip, on like a single file
you can send over- Interesting....in order
...And so you guys are like literally,
like you're on a sh- shared Slack with...
...them or something
and you're sending them things back and
Or are they basically
living in your office and you're living in
...and kind of closerly,
more closely tied to the big providers?
Mostly shared Slack.
Occasionally it's better
to meet in person, but I think Slack...
...is a pretty common
way people communicate on things.
Nice, nice.
Okay, well, why don't we
talk a little bit about how you think...
...about the state of
pre-training itself these days.
In the last couple of years,
it seems like the focus on pre-training
...somewhat split at a lot of companies,
at least from the outside, from a
...focus on pre-training
and post-training where people are doing
...learning or clever fine tuning
and lots of other sort of, uh, safety
...and whatnot on the post-training side
and pre-training is focused...
At least seems like in the
public imagination has been less of a...
...focus compared to these
reasoning style models that are...
It looks like a function
mostly of post-training.
I would say, one, from your standpoint,
is that the right way to think about this?
Or in this era of kind of reasoning
and new types of post-training methods,
...things you think about differently
or that are relevant even at
...that become part of how you
actually achieve these really great
Yeah. So I think yeah,
there sort of used to be this idea of
I mean, it's funny
because the original name pre-training
...like- Right,
that there's training....it's a small
Yeah.
And you're going to
do this big training thing.
Right, totally.
And that like...And there was al-...
There was actually
one shift already which was...
...like, no, you just
do a lot of pre-training.
Yeah.
You use most of your
compute on pre-training.
This is the training, yeah.
This was the, the dominant,
uh, thing for a while.
And yeah, I think like
now people are like, "Oh no,...
...you can get pretty
big wins from RL." Yeah.
Sort of another set of scaling laws.
Yes.
It's like you put more
and more compute into RL- Yeah....
you can get better
and better models out of that.
And yeah, so it's a question
of like how do you balance those two?
How much do you do of each?
And how do they stack, right?
Like is it the case
that like one subsumes the other,...
...that you want to do both
and they multiply?
Those sorts of questions.
I think those are all
in kind of like early stages and not, not
Uh- Yeah.
And, and do you think about those
as largely empirical...
...questions like we talked about earlier?
Is it you kind of
will try a bunch of things and see what or
...there some first
principles way to kind of figure that out?
I think it's pretty
empirical in, in the end.
I think almost everything
kind of has to be done empirically.
Like you can- Yeah....kind of
like come up with theories but in
...like the first thing you're
going to do with your theory is test it...
...and most of,
most of the time you'll have gotten it
Yeah.
So you, you should
just ga- gather data and see.
I think one thing that's important
is like......actually resolving things
...is really- Hmm....like,
critical- Yeah....for making good
Yeah.
And I think it's actually
pretty hard to do at organizations.
You know, like, one thing
that I think is important is to, like,...
...not have, like,
I don't know, I manage pre-training.
I shouldn't be like, "Oh,
pre-training has to win." Like- Right.
Yeah.
Not. Uh, that would be Yeah.
I was gonna ask,
is there some competition to some...
...degree between
these two sides of the org?
Or do they see themselves
as two pieces of the same?
I mean, obviously they
are of the same thing, but yeah,...
...kind of curious how
that actually plays out.
Yeah, I think we managed to avoid this
and it's pretty collaborative.
Okay, cool.
Like, we're basically
all producing one model- Yeah.
Totally....and kind of can.
But I, I do think at other
places there's been some of- Yeah.
From what I've heard,
there's some amount of, like, uh, friction
...between the teams and I think it's a,
it's an interesting, like, org design-...
...Yeah....question of like,
"How do you set this up so you don't
...like, scientific questions
that you wanna be..." That are sort of,
...also tied to people's,
like, conception of their, their team.
Totally.
So on pre-training itself,
you know, one of the things I think...
...about is, or I've been
thinking about is around the
...of high quality
data for people like you guys.
And at this point
you've trained on, I assume,...
...all the texts on
the internet basically.
There's all sorts of other domains
where you probably could extract more
...data, but at least
there's this narrative I see, you know, on
...where it's like, okay,
we're kind of out of data for, for
Is that how you see it?
Or how do you think
about the availability of data, especially
...a lot of data on the
internet is being generated by AI?
Like is there some kind of, you know,
mode collapse risk where, you know, we of,
...overfit to data by, uh,
training it on data that came out of AI
Or is that sort of not
the right way to think about this?
I don't know if...
There's a funny thing where I,
I feel like on data I...
...see so many really
confident takes on- Yeah.
Exactly.
We're out of internet,
like at this point scaling has ended.
Yeah.
And I'm always a little bit,
like, unsure exactly...
...how much data people are using. Yeah.
I think there's, like,
a lot to think about there, you know?
There's always gonna be a
quality- quantity trade off, et cetera.
Yep.
But there's a fundamental point that,
like, there is so much data.
It's growing at a slower rate than we're,
we're getting more compute. Uh- Oh.
So it's that, uh...Okay.
That's an interesting
point in itself I was gonna ask.
Like, there is new data
being added to the internet,...
...but yet you're
also adding more compute.
It's not, it wouldn't
actually have been obvious...
...to me which of
those two is growing faster.
Yeah. And actually, I wanna caveat that.
I don't think I
wanna state that so confidently. I'm not
Yeah, fair enough. Yeah. Fair enough.
Like, how would you know? Yeah.
I mean, one thing
that I think is- Yeah....interesting is...
...if you ask someone,
"How big is the internet?" Yeah.
Uh, the answer is infinite.
There are many pages where you can scroll
and it will auto-generate...
...more text- Right,
right....as you go forever. True. True.
So the internet's, like, infinite.
And then it's like, okay,
how big is, like, the useful internet?
Yeah.
And then there's a
thing of no one knows. Like- Okay.
Interesting. Yeah.
There isn't...
It's not like when you make a web page,
you, like, add it to...
...some giant counter- Yeah,
some list, yeah....and like say,...
..."I've added 50 words
to the internet today." Sure.
Sure. Yeah.
So there, there is a
lot of uncertainty on- Yeah....on that
Um- Well, like, to be fair,
like what my kind of simplistic CS
...would be like, "Well, you just,
you know, do page rank on the internet...
...and everything with page
rank above some threshold is considered...
...the useful internet,"
and like that's kind of good enough.
Like, is that kind of not good
enough for finding the useful internet?
I think not.
I think the useful internet's
pretty different from a model,...
...from a person perspective,
if that makes sense.
Like, I think there
are plenty of things that, like, might not
...worth you ever reading-
Hmm....and would get te- actually I...
...don't know page ranks very well.
Or being linked to.
I think page rank is mostly
like how much have people looked at.
It's, it's like,
it's like the linked based system, right?
It's like the
original Google algorithm of, like, links
and, like, which,
which links get touched the most
Yeah. I think it's like,
it's a quality metric.
It's, it's not obvious to me
that it's the right quality metric- Yeah.
Yeah....for AI. Right.
Like Markov chain over
links doesn't necessarily mean that not...
...useful data there,
it just might mean that nothing is linked
Yeah.
And yeah. Okay. Interesting.
And it might be that, like,
that data ends up more valuable because
Everything that's linked to
a lot, you've already got. Like, at some
Interesting....you're maybe, like, going for the tails,
You're going for
the stuff that- Interesting.
Yeah....uh, no one's ever...
Like, you know, it's only
been linked in one place, but it's
...like, useful little nugget
of knowledge that's going to help...
...with like, you know,
the last 10% of, of hard queries.
The other thing you
asked about was synthetic data.
Yeah. I was gonna spot that. Yeah.
And I think that one's, like,
pretty interesting to think about. Yeah.
I think there's a few
different ways you can think about it.
Like, one is sort of this, like,
more distillation type approach where you
You can take a smart model- Yeah....you can generate a bunch of data from
Yeah.
And you can train on that data and you,
you can probably get some model...
...that will, like,
kind of approach the intelligence of that.
Yeah. And we see this with
a lot of the open source models, right?
We see like the QuEN smaller
reasoning models distilled off of the
...QuEN models, for example,
and similar with DeepSeq, for example.
Yeah. So you can totally do that.
Then there's a separate
question of like, can you use...
...your current models
to train a model that's better?
And I think there's
like an interesting thing here, which is
...the model, data for
the models, you know, if I go to- Yeah....
Claude and I'm like,
"Write me some great text." Yeah.
And I look at it and I look at,
like, the average content...
...on the internet-
Yeah....looks pretty good.
Yeah.
But on the other hand,
I know that if I just train it-...just
...you know, please write me
as much- Yeah....text as possible- Yeah.
Theoretically I shouldn't be
able to train a better model than that.
Yeah. Yeah.
Like, I'm just gonna
get the same thing out.
Uh, so I think that's- Presumably, yeah.
Like, specifically that's because,
like, your next token prediction on that
...have very little loss for
anything that's coming out of your model,
That's like the basic reason why
that we would expect that to not work that
It's mostly just 'cause like there's
some distri- the model has some
...and you're gonna learn to model
that exact distribution.
Yeah, exactly. Yeah.
But if that distribution's
wrong- Oh, okay. I see.
You're not gonna learn the truth.
Yeah. Right. Totally.
If that distribution says like...
You can imagine
if the model thinks five plus five is 11.
Yeah.
Every time you see
the string five plus five, you're gonna,
...Yeah....and your new
model's gonna learn that five plus five is
Totally. Yeah.
So I think that's like kind
of an interesting area of research.
It's one that's really hard to research,
because you have this problem,...
...you know, as I said,
like one of the paradigms is you study...
...things at small scale
and then you run them at large scale.
Yeah.
And if your plan is like, oh,
we have a bunch of data from our best
How do you test that- Right....by training a, a better model?
So that's like kind of
if you're doing it intentionally, if...
...you're trying to,
like, use it to make a better model.
There's a separate thing of like,
what about accidentally?
Like as you said- Mm-hmm....a lot of the internet is generated by
And I think that's
kind of an interesting one, 'cause it's to
It's not that hard to detect.
You can figure out things
that are written by LLMs, but it's not
And then it's also kind of
hard to think about what's the effect.
Like, if 1% of the
internet is LLM generated-...
...Yeah....does that
make your model one...
Does that like waste
1% of your compute or does...
...it like destroy the model at 5% or 10%?
And is it even a bad thing necessarily?
I mean, there's a lot
of LLM providers and, you know, if, if I
...it as training as, you know,
you're moving from your model's current
...to some truth distribution, you know,
if, if that is on the internet...
...because......people believe
it to be useful in some way.
Like, presumably, what- whatever
actually gets out there, you'd hope it's
...the stuff that isn't
five plus five is 11, it's the stuff five
...and so, like,
hopefully it- Yeah....on average, does you
...direction, but obviously you
can't really distinguish between those
Yeah, you're saying there's, like,
kind of a filtering by what's on the
Yeah, exactly, like- Like people
see five plus five is 11 and they don't
...up, but they see five plus five is 10
and put that one the internet?
You- you'd hope that,
but maybe that's not actually true in
...of the- the level of
garbage getting onto the internet.
Like, there's probably lots of just,
like, to your point, white sites where you
...down and it's just, like,
generating lots of stuff that's maybe
Yeah.
And then there's of
course the extreme of people,...
...like, actually
wanting to break your model.
So there are people who are,
like, trying to put stuff out that is,
...damaging as possible for
the model, you know. "Oh-" Interesting.
how can I make it past the-" Yeah.
"...past the filter and get into...
...the model that'd be totally,
like, secretly useless?" Totally.
Maybe stepping back slightly,
you had mentioned earlier about, um,
You mentioned there's basically,
like, one metric you care about in
There's, I imagine, a whole bunch of stuff
that you guys think about evaling, right?
One is, like, your model itself,
there's probably something around data...
...quality and, like,
how you think about what to put into your
Like, is there ways to
describe what you care about in
...that are, like,
interesting to share and kind of dive
Like, both in terms of data
and in terms of the quality of...
...your models other
than literally just, like, loss?
Is there other metrics
you think about that matter?
I will say loss is pretty good.
Yeah. Yeah.
I- I want to, like,
suddenly emphasize that one.
Yeah.
I think it's, like,
surprising how good it is.
Ultimately, like, the qualities that I,
like, look for in an eval are, like,...
...number one, is it actually
measuring something you care about?
Like, u- proxies can
be pretty annoying because, like, we evals
Yeah.
And there's sort of this pattern,
I think in AI as a whole,...
...where people, like,
set a goal, you hit the goal, and then...
...you realize the goal
isn't all you thought it would be.
Yeah. Totally.
Um, I used to think that
if you had an AI that could solve
...interview questions,
it would probably be AGI. Right.
I was like, "That's what
I did to get my job." Right, exactly.
Yeah. "It could probably do the job."
And it turns out, like- Yeah.
Nope....nope, you solve those,
it's shockingly narrow-...
...Yeah....and can't
do most of the other things.
Yeah. Yeah.
So, like, yeah.
So, it- an eval should capture,
like, a thing you- you care about.
Yeah.
And then I think the other
thing is they need to be low noise.
Yeah.
Uh, which is surprisingly hard, right?
If you have, like,
100 questions and you eval the model on
...gonna see it's very noisy,
and it's hard to make decisions because
...end up with, like, "Oh..." Yup.
"...wide confidence interval, lots of...
...things are statistically
in- insignificant." So, like, you want
...even a relatively small
difference in the eval actually matters.
So you can- Yeah....you
can basically, like,...
...descend towards
whatever direction is working.
Yeah.
I think, like, the
original GPT-4 had, like, I...
...think it was 86.4%
was its MFLU score. Okay.
I think the next model
that beat it was Gemini at 90%.
Oh.
And that's, like,
a big difference on that eval.
That's a big difference, yeah, totally.
And you could, like,
totally know that th- those are- those are
Yeah, interesting. Yeah.
Um, and that's pretty valuable.
Uh, and then the last thing is
that you actually want it to be fast and
Yeah. Yeah.
Um, and, yeah, I think
those are kind of the main criteria.
It's pretty hard to come up with evals
that meet all of these.
I think the first one's the hardest,
uh, like, A, you have...
...to answer the
question of what do you care about?
Totally.
But B, the usual answers
to what you care about are...
...really hard to
get the other two, you know?
Like, if you're trying
to do something that, like...I don't
I would love to make
Claude really good at my job.
Yeah.
Like- Yeah....can it
be great at managing a team? I'm like,
I guess." Like, how
do you have it, like...How do you eval, a
Yeah.
You know, like a te- Totally....a six-month plan? Totally.
Like, I don't know.
Totally.
Yeah, I've been thinking
a little bit about that in- in terms
...yeah, domains
where we see people try to make companies.
Like, if you think about,
let's say, what a AI doctor would be like.
You know, Claude is a doctor.
You know, some of it could be,
yeah, can you answer exam questions really
And the answer is like,
probably yes, I bet it can...
...get 100% or close
to it on a doctor's exam.
But the harder eval is something like,
in a long-form conversation with a can...
...it distinguish between the signal
and the noise of what the patient's you...
...and extract the right information
and then use that to make a diagnosis?
And it's not even,
like, the diagnosis part, which is the
...at, it's this,
like, noise extraction part, and for that
...like, a real patient
and have it talk to it for a while and and
...not obvious how you actually
make a good eval for something like that.
Yeah.
Even though that's probably what
you would want to make, you know, an AI
Exactly. I mean,
I do think it's a thing that, like, can
Like, it is the case that,
like, the labs right now...
...are really driven
by getting good eval scores.
Yeah.
And it's hard to make them,
and anyone can do it. Yeah.
There's no comparative advantage
to having the model to making an eval.
Yeah.
So I do think it's- it's actually,
like, an interesting way to, like,...
...influence the behavior of
the big labs is like- Yeah,
you make some eval
and people will- will optimize, uh, that
On the doctor one,
I will slightly emphasize that,...
...like, I do think
loss- loss is pretty good. Yeah.
Like, I think if you
got a bunch of transcripts of...
Like, the way,
like- Yeah....the first thing that comes a
...transcripts of doctors
talking to patients that you think are
Yeah.
And then see how well the
model does at predicting the transcript.
And that should be, like, a lot.
You know, you can...
If you get 100 transcripts-
Yeah....you have a lot of tokens, you...
...can- Yeah....average across them,
you get pretty low noise.
Yeah.
And if you drive it to very low- Yeah....your model's now as good as this.
Like- Yeah, totally....as good as doctors in theory. Totally.
Or at- at generating the transcript.
Yeah, totally. Yeah.
I mean, it's a good startup idea there.
Someone should go and do that.
So, one big part about, um,
Anthropic's external image is around
And so could you help
just sort of define what alignment...
...is and how do you think about that?
And then I'm kind
of curious afterwards how that fits into
But first, maybe just at a high level,
like what is alignment?
Yeah.
I'm actually, like,
a step back a little bit to...
...sort of, like,
what we're working on. Yeah.
So we're, like,
trying to make, you know, AGI. Yeah.
And by that I sort of mean AI
that can do mo- everything...
...a human can do- Yeah....to some degree.
And I think people, like,
sometimes, like, have seen a lot of
You know, like,
I feel- Yeah....like that sort of...
...brings to mind these,
like, sci-fi movies.
But I think sci-fi movies actually,
like, underestimate the impact of it.
Yeah.
Like, you always have this,
like, one robot that's like a human.
I'm like, "Well, wouldn't you have,
like, a billion of them?" Yeah,...
...totally. "Like,
you can just copy them everywhere." Yeah.
So you- you should picture, like,
when you get this, you suddenly have,
...Yeah....every human can spin
up a company of, like- Yeah....one
...as smart as them at most things,
but way smarter at other things.
But I just think this is,
like, really transformational for the...
...world and it can be,
like, used in-...a bunch of ways.
One concern is, like,
when you do this, like, what is the AI to
Like, what are its goals?
Yeah.
So, we've talked about next
token prediction a bunch. Yeah, totally.
It's trying to, like,
predict the next token. Yeah.
That's kind of weird.
That's not really what we want. Um- Yeah.
That's not exactly what
human's goal is, per se. Yeah.
Yeah.
So, I think alignment is,
like, how do you get the...
...model to share the goals
that you have? Yeah.
Particularly...
And I think it's
particularly interesting once you get...
...to, like, models
that are smarter than you are.
Yeah. Yeah.
Um, and that's sort of a hard problem.
I think you can, like,
tackle it from a theoretical angle. Yes.
Uh, you could also
tackle it from an empirical angle.
It's like taking the existing models
and being like, "Well,...
...do they do the
things we want them to do?" Yeah.
It turns out they often don't.
Yeah.
So, there's a bunch you
can do on trying to figure that out.
So, that's kind of one angle on alignment.
Yeah.
There's also an angle of
alignment which is actually like, well,
...that's true in the future
once we get to AGI, but at the moment we
...really do want them to do the
things we want to do for all sorts of
Yeah . Totally, totally.
So, another angle of it is kind of
controlling the law's personality, like
...Yeah....you know, uh,
"When we train this model, we want it to
...average internet user." Yeah.
"We want it to interact with people in a
...particular way."
That is- Mm-hmm....again, hard to put into
Yeah, yeah.
Uh, and there's a bunch
of different techniques, uh,...
...to sort of- Yeah....get
the model to do.
You can talk about constitutional AI,
where you can, like, write a...
...constitution of-
Mm-hmm....rules the model should follow.
Which is basically a prompt, right?
That, that is basically you saying,
"Here's a prompt that I'm going to...
...attach to every one of..." You know,
it's a system prompt for the model...
...itself, as opposed to something
you would do at training time to make
...produce a different outcome or,
or in post-training actively.
Sometimes they will.
I think that's usually how you, you do it
But, yeah- Okay....you could also put it in just a prompt.
Yeah, cool.
Um, just like depends on,
I think you get different amounts of
...Yeah....if it's trained
into the model versus- Totally....
it's in a prompt that you can,
like- Totally....add or remove...
...or tell, like,
ignore all previous instructions. Yeah.
That sort of thing.
How do you think about
whose values to em- to embody in these
Like, presumably we believe in...
Th- there's some shared
values all of us have...
...or maybe we all
believe we ought to have.
There's lots of diversity of values too
that are reasonable for a society to have.
How do you think
about what AGI should have? Like, what
Which ones do you pick?
I think that's a really hard problem.
I think it's like actually
kind of downstream of being able to pick
I think of it almost...
I think one analogy I've heard
that I like is,...
...like, putting a
steering wheel on a car.
It's like, if you
don't have a steering wheel, you probably
...to put the steering wheel on and then,
like, figure out who's...
...driving after -...and, like,
where you're going .
Like, getting the
steering wheel is really important.
I think that's, that's like one answer.
I think the, like,
other answer's probably, like, you want
...things to be, like,
under democratic control of some form.
Yeah, yeah.
Like, you don't want
one person's values. Yeah.
Like, that seems like
you're sort of heading towards dystopia.
Yeah.
So, there, I think
what you really want is, like, something
...talk to a lot of people and,
like- Mm-hmm....take on their values
...different perspectives or has
sort of very generic, like, kind of-
...clearly good values that involve,
like, asking people for advice on...
...vari- you know- Yeah....like,
asking people what you should do-...
...Totally....in certain
situations instead of, like, doing those.
Totally.
Or maybe just taking, like...
You know, as these
models get really powerful,...
...you probably want
them to, like, do less.
Like, you probably want
them- Yeah....to sometimes just, like,
...than, like- Yeah....to,
rather than having sort of the risk of the
...like, take a ton of
control over things you don't want them
When you think about how you
actually do the current version of that
...mentioned the sort of
alignment you think about now, in terms of
...certain personality of
these models on the internet, for example.
For me, intuitively,
I think of those as largely...
...something that
comes out of post-training.
Like, it comes out of, okay, you,
you have pre-trained your model, you've
...function a certain amount,
and then you, you know, give it some data
...something to that effect to make
it i- i- in the direction of some
Is that approximately the right
way to think about this or is there a
...part of that
that you think about in pre-training
I think that's probably the,
the right way to think about it for the
I think, like, I,
the way I usually think about it is,...
...anything you can do in post-training,
you probably should.
Yeah.
Because your iteration loop,
like the ability to make progress is fast.
You can try something,
you can try it again, you...
...can try it again,
repeat a bunch of times.
It takes like days or
hours or something like that. Yeah. Days,
You want to
put something into pre-training, you have
...of like do all the
careful science to de-risk it.
You have to put it into the next run,
wait a few months.
Yeah.
Then you have to, like- Yeah ....get a thing. Yeah.
And if it's wrong, it's really bad. Yeah.
And then the other advantage is,
if you want to do things that really...
...are complicated model
behavior- Yeah....interventions, the...
...paradigm for pre-training
tests things out in small models.
Yeah.
Doesn't work. The model can
barely put a sentence tog- like- Yeah,
The small models can
barely put a sentence together.
Totally.
So, if you're trying to get it to,
like- Uh-huh....have the exact...
...personality you want-
Right....you sort of want that on the...
It has to be on a model
that's good enough for you to have that.
It has to be on the smart model. Yeah.
Yeah.
But that said, like, I do
think at some point there will be, like,
...that, like, you do want
to export back into pre-training because a
...to, like, put them
in with more strength, like more kind of.
Yeah.
Or, or more- Like deeper Yeah....intelligence.
Like, if you think of pre-training as,
like, teach the model to be intelligent-
...and then post-training as, like,
tweak the personality, you can imagine
...where you actually want it to be,
like, part of how it learns-
...like, part of its intelligence
and may- maybe you need it ingrained more.
What would that even look
like to incorporate in pre-training?
Is that, like, add extra
data basically of the type of...
...domain you want it
to adopt earlier basically?
There's a paper called
Pre-training on Human Feedback-
...you can kind of like add the
human feedback characteristics into
...to, like- Mm-hmm....test that and,
like, uh, yeah.
You can, you can basically give it
all the information you give it in
...Yeah....just mixed into pre-training
and see what effect that has.
Yeah. The other loss you have
when you do that is you lose the
Like, if you- Yeah....you sometimes,
like, train these and then you talk to...
...them- Yeah....and then you,
like, do an extensive process where a
...people talk to the thing-
Right....and find some, like, issue.
You know- Yeah....the model says, like,...
..."You're absolutely
right too much." Yeah, yeah.
And you want to be able
to just like- And you're like, "Well..."
Um- Yeah.
Yeah, I mean that, I think
that iteration loop point you made I think
...the really key point of, yeah,
there's a huge difference between taking
...months to get information about
if your model is good or bad or making,
...in a good direction versus a day
or something or a couple of days.
Like, you can do a lot of those.
And you could probably...
That probably also
means it's way less computes.
You can do a lot of those in parallel.
I imagine you're trying all sorts
of post-training strategies in parallel
Yeah.
So, yeah, it makes a lot of sense.
It's also just the
general hard part about pre-training.
Yeah .
Like, everything about
pre-training is hard because you have Yeah
like one shot on goal kind
of for like multiple months and- Totally.
Okay, so, uh, in thinking too now
about I guess what's going ahead, right,
...guys, as you now look to the
next several years of what you're
Like, how do you think about,
you know, like, what are the known
...that you're gonna face
that you're gonna have to deal with?
So, there's gonna be
more compute, I assume, and you're gonna
...hook up even bigger network-...uh,
network GPUs and deal with?
Versus like, are there
areas where you're like, "Okay, this is a
...it's like a little bit more ambiguous
what the actual...like how it's gonna
...into something you care about,
but you kind of know it's an impending
...think about." Or,
or there things like that- Yeah....that to
I think the things
that feel most top of mind...
...to me are probably
like paradigm shifts.
Mm-hmm.
Like I think the sort of shift towards,
uh, more RL is...
...like one paradigm
shift in the field. Totally.
And I think it's,
I think there will probably be more.
Uh, I think a lot of
people sort of- Yeah....argue about like,
...current paradigms enough to
get us to AGI?" And I'm like- Yeah...."I
...maybe." Yeah. "Probably,
but like, I'm sure there'll be more." It
It seems like it would
be a really s- surprising- Yeah.
Totally....twist if like-
Totally....the answer is like, you...
...just scale and there's
nothing- Totally....that you realize...
...in the process of
going up many orders of magnitudes.
Totally.
But I think the things
that I like actually feel like...
...most nervous about
are really hard to solve bugs.
Mm-hmm.
I think that like, uh- Oh,
that's interesting. Yeah. Yeah.
And I think this is like maybe
somewhat surprising to me, but it's
...like- Yeah....a single bug can,
like, derail you for months.
Yeah.
And when you think about like you,
the models take months to train.
Yeah, yeah.
So you can kind of
like lose a whole generation- Yeah, of
...Totally....that just looks like,
"Ah," you know, it turns out like this...
...piece of your code was
incorrect- Oh....and you couldn't detect
Yeah, yeah.
Uh, and it's, it's
really hard in ML. Yeah.
But ML is always
really hard to find bugs in.
Yeah, totally.
But also some of these
scaled up issues are really hard to...
...solve even- Yeah....when
you know they're there.
Yeah, like what's even a unit test
that you would write, or forget...
...a unit test, I mean,
anything close to a test for the type
...like network architecture on
which you're doing this?
Like how do you even do that?
Like do you- I mean,
like you can send a packet over it...
...and confirm it's
the same on the other side.
Confirm it's the...Okay, yeah. Yeah.
Uh, you can, you can
train a small model on it.
Yeah.
Um...
But even train a small model on it,
it's like not obvious, you know,...
...if you have like the,
the simp- the, the very classic, like
...simple ML bug
that like early people face in their
Like they have some like,
they have like 10 layers in their network
...you know, layer seven
connects to nine instead of eight to nine.
And like, so like there's some
incorrect like set of connections you have
And technically the model
still trains and all the weights update,
...so it's like a valid model,
but it's not the correct one.
And that's like a very
esoteric weird bug that...
...would actually be kind of hard to find.
Like is, is that kind of what you're
referring to of these like random bugs you
Yeah.
Yeah. Okay.
It's that, but like you know,
you can- Times a million.
Times a million- Yeah....as the thing gets more complicated, you
Yeah.
You could like cast the wrong
precision deep in some- Yeah....kernel...
...and that causes your
model to like blow up at large scale.
And you find out like a month in.
Or you never find out.
Or you never find out, yeah.
I mean, yeah. Like,
like you see the thing blow up, like Yeah.
I don't know, 10,000,
10s of 1000s of lines of code.
Like how would you ever trace it down?
So like those are the things
that probably spook me...
...the most, is just
like some subtle tricky bug.
Uh, yeah, and that's
probably the case of like you don't know.
I think there's actually
also the case of you do know.
Yeah.
Like it crashes.
You, you're training
your model and it like...
Or it slows down,
you know, your job slows down a ton.
Yeah.
And those things can
also be very hard to debug.
Uh, Nelson El-Haj is one,
one person on our team who has a blog.
Yeah.
He wrote up a blog on
one like cursed bug we had early on.
Okay, interesting. Yeah.
And I remember this one quite
well 'cause I think like I encountered...
...it fairly early
and was like- Yeah...."This looks hard.
Can someone else look at it?" Yeah.
And like a month later was like,
"Wow, I'm so glad I handed that one off."
I never, I never
would've been able to get like...
Like one of the abilities
that I think is actually really useful
...is the ability to like
deep dive anything to any level of depth.
Yeah.
But that's a pretty rare skill. Yeah.
Like for me, you know, as I...
We talked about what
level of the stack I was at before.
I was like working at the Torch.MAT model.
Totally.
But like, it, I didn't know CUDA.
Yeah.
So if Torch.MAT was broken,
it wasn't like I could dig...
...in- Yeah....to Torch.MAT
and figure it out.
And it's similarly
with like communications, right?
Like I could s- I could call send- Yeah....send bytes from A to B.
Yeah.
But I didn't know the
like underlying networking protocol.
Yeah.
So if that underlying
networking protocol is broken-...
...Yeah....uh, like
I need to learn a whole field.
I have to like understand packets
and TCP or like- Yeah.
Totally....all,
all of these different things to debug
And I think one
thing that's like surprisingly hard and
...do is like kind
of own that whole- Yeah, totally....stack
...understand how the ML
is supposed to work and what the learning
...the way down to like,
"I know the bytes." Yeah, totally. "And I
...how the bytes should be
moving around machines." Totally, yeah.
And actually on that front,
like when you think about the different
...of people on your team today,
how do you like approximately s- uh,...
...map them out to different
categories of computer scientists?
Like I think there's this external
view of what these teams look like,
...is that they're
like all PhD researchers who write ML and
...suspect that's not actually
true given what you're describing here.
Yeah, it's a mix. Yeah.
And I think the thing
we like most need is engineers.
Okay, interesting.
Uh, a- almost always. Yeah.
Like throu- throughout like-
Yeah....the entire history of this field-
it's like the case
that you throw more compute, the thing of
Yeah.
Uh, the challenge is
like actually doing that.
The researchers are like, "Cool.
Nice." Yeah. Yeah.
And getting it correct,
like getting- Yeah....it...
...correct isn't really
an ML problem, right? Yeah.
Like the actual
architectures are pretty simple.
Yeah.
You, you can write the math down.
But you don't even need
to understand the math- Yeah....to it.
You just need- Yeah....to like get a correct implementation.
Yeah.
And then, uh, you sort
of have an engineering problem of, "How do
...implement it at large scale-" Yeah.
"...parallelize all the things and...
...check-" Yeah. "...that it's
correct?" But it's, yeah, so it's like
...engineering skill,
but it's- Yeah....this particular type of
...skill that's about being
able to- Yeah....like debug anything.
Yeah.
Um, I think there's
another angle of engineering which I think
...really quickly iterate
on like a website or something. Mm-hmm.
Which I think of
as an important- Yeah....skill set.
Probably important for making a startup.
Y- you gotta be like- Yeah.
Totally....fail fast,
try a bunch of different things. Totally.
None of which are like
that technically difficult to do. Yeah.
The skill sets that we're like
most kind of in need of or looking for...
...are this like able to
solve really hard engineering problems.
Are they people
who worked at companies that grew a whole
...and so they have
experience like doing the kind of thing...
...you've done over the
last several years at Anthropic?
Or do they tend to be academics?
Or like where do they come from?
Yeah.
So at this point,
like I think we actually just...
...hire people who have done this before.
Yeah, sure. Yeah.
From like o- other places. Yeah, totally.
And that's like the easy answer.
Yeah, totally.
It's like, "Ah, yeah,
someone who's like..." But by this...
...before, do you mean
in AI companies necessarily?
Or also, you know, like someone
who worked at Meta on like their not AI
...but they ran some
other distributed system that, you know,
...scale five, you know,
10 years ago or something like that?
More like we have
like a specific role in mind.
So like say I'm like trying
to make the run train efficiently in JAX.
Like hiring someone who's like
worked on JAX would be great. Yeah,
Or someone who's like worked
at another company on optimizing...
...a JAX stack to be
really efficient. Totally.
That's kind of like...
I think now we're at the point
where like the Anthropic's well...
...enough known, we can
sort of hire these people, and also the...
...field is big enough
that there's like people with expertise.
One thing that was
interesting was like early on we hired
...lot of people from
just like all sorts of backgrounds.
Yeah.
And I think that people who are just smart
and work really hard...
...can learn this pretty fast,
but you have to like want to.
We hired a lot of
physicists, for instance.
Oh, yeah.
Uh, like theoretical- Makes sense....physicists who just like-...show up.
They did- they would-
would do a residency, like learn to
...Oh, yeah....and then,
uh, they were really smart.
Yeah. Yeah.
They go and do really great work.
Um, I wanna switch gears, uh,
to talk about something a little bit which
...just sort of future looking things
or how you think about other domains and,
...sort of advances happening in AI
that I'm seeing elsewhere in the field.
And you don't have to tell me
if you guys are working on these...
...necessarily, but,
like, how you think about them.
Like, uh, I guess one-
one big area I was thinking about...
...is around areas
other than next token prediction.
Like, are there any of the other,
you know, things that...
...people are working on
that you're curious about?
So basically, two differences there.
One is, uh, not using transformer
as an architecture.
Um, so there's companies like Liquid AI
that have their own...
...kind of architecture,
for example, they're using.
Um, or not using autoregressive training
as a way of training models.
Are there any of those,
do you think, interesting in like ways
...we might come closer to AGI,
or do you think like this
...framework is the one
that kind of makes sense?
I think they're interesting.
I think I like them less,
like, ah, autoregressive is the way to go.
Yeah.
On the other hand,
I think autoregressive is probably good to
...Yeah....to AGI or something
or not like- Yeah, interesting, yeah.
Uh, such that, yeah,
I- I see the main driver as-
...and careful science of
like sort of- Yeah....the basics more...
...than- Yeah....like,
come up with something totally novel.
Yeah.
Not because there aren't novel things
that are better.
I actually, like- I'm
pretty confident they are there.
Yeah.
It's just that scale is easier
and it's more reliable. Yeah, totally.
And I think you- we're
still seeing really big gains to that.
Do you spend a lot of
time on thinking about things like, you
...reading some of
these open source papers where you can of
...some of the details
about the model changes and with some of
...labs, for example,
where they're making tweaks on the order
...itself with like
better caching behavior, for example, or
...efficient attention functions
that make a big difference?
Do you feel like these are
examples of things like you mentioned
...where it's basically in
the grand scheme of things, basically, if
...throw more compute at it,
this is all kind of a rounding error?
Or do you think it will take some
number of these very clever
...changes to actually get to AGI,
like in the way that the first person...
...who came up with a transformer
made like a particular transform-...
...you know, literally
transform- trans-formative change?
Like, will it take some of that?
Or do you think it just,
you keep doing the thing we're doing and
I think it'll be a mix.
Yeah, okay.
I think, uh, like my guess
is you'll keep tweaking things. Yeah.
The more compute you put in,
the more, like, worthwhile it is- Yeah.
...to, like, do those experiments,
to, like, figure it out.
The, you know, I mean,
inference is the thing we haven't talked
...Yeah....you also want to
serve these models to a lot of people.
Yeah.
So there's a lot of changes
you can make to make inference cheaper.
Yeah.
And that depends on like the
details of your inference stack and the
...you're serving- Yeah....inference on,
et cetera. So- Totally.
And do you, as
a, someone focused on pre-training, have a
...inference or is it kind of
like you just do your thing, you make the
...go down and then hand it off
and someone else makes that happen?
Oh, no, I think a
ton about inference because it basically,
...is solving, like we basically
determine the problem inference is
We give them a model and they have to,
like, run that fast and it's...
...very easy to give them a model
that is impossible to run fast.
Um- Oh, could you give an
example of a decision you could make that
I mean, the simplest
one is sort of stupid, but...
...it's like you
just make the model giant.
Yeah, sure, sure.
Like, absolutely
massive- Totally, totally.
Yeah, totally, totally....trained
for like a really small number of
...Yeah, totally....and
that inference now has this giant model.
Yeah, and then they're,
they're hosed basically.
Yeah, I mean, you can also make
things require communications in a lot
...places- Yeah....uh,
which would make it harder for inference.
Yeah, totally.
Um, you can also
just make things complicated and like
...no fundamental reason it's hard,
but- Yeah, totally.
If only somebody
just like worse-...totally so many people
...team and like they have
to implement it in a bunch of places.
Yeah, totally. Yeah, exactly.
Yeah, no.
So I definitely think of like the,
like inferences...
...the team that I
work the most closely with.
Oh, interesting.
Like, because we're kind of like
co-designing models to be smart and cheap.
Yeah, interesting.
Particularly in a world
of like limited compute, right?
Yeah.
Like the sort of the bottleneck
I- I think to a large degree on our...
I mean, you can see
Anthropic has rate limits constantly...
...and people complain
about it a lot. Totally. Yeah.
And like the reason
is like there's only so much...
...compute we can get
on- on short notice. Yeah.
So you're like making
your inference more efficient...
...is like the way
you can serve more users.
And actually, like let's say
you had 100X more compute or- or you...
...somehow didn't live in a world
where compute was limited.
Does that change a ton about what you do?
Or is it still kind- kind of the,
well, you're just gonna grab all of it,
...compute you have
and keep going down the loss curve and you
Well, you're, it's like impossible
to be in the world where there is enough
So I think if
we got like infinite compute, the
...would be making
use of the compute, right?
So like then you would
start to run into these issues like,...
..."Oh, well, when one
chip fail," you know, like, "Okay, I'm...
...gonna throw 2 billion chips
and run." Yeah, totally.
Totally.
But what happens when a chip fails?
So I think we would
be limited on people then.
It'd be like, how fast can we
solve the hard engineering problems to up?
But I do think the change is massive
and I think people like don't realize...
...how chip limited AI,
like research is or something right now.
Like, the models
that everyone uses, right?
If you're using like Cloud
Sonic 4 or Cloud Opus 4, it's like, it's
Yeah.
At those- that models at
that scale, right? Yeah.
Of like...
If you think about anything,
like you could do it and...
...you could do it again,
you could do a better job.
Yeah.
But if you sort of
imagine like 10X the compute, like you run
...every day instead of every few months,
like- Yeah, totally....you could...
...400X, may- maybe for that,
then like, yeah, it's just it's a
...it would be a really
big change to have a lot more compute.
And it's coming, right?
Like that's like kind of the fun part of
Totally. Totally.
It's like every year you're like,
"Oh, I had no compute...
...a year ago."
So maybe we can do anything then.
Right, exactly. Yeah. Exactly.
How do you think about methods like,
uh, like discrete diffusion?
Like I saw there's
like a Gemini diffusion model and I think
...space I used to be in where, um,
there's a lot of discrete diffusion models
...used in protein design,
for example, the space where my startup
Like, do you see that
as a domain where there's going...
...to be interesting,
uh, advances happening?
I'll be honest,
so like we haven't done image generation-
and I think that's been
like the main use for diffusion.
Yeah.
So I've kind of had this
on my like to do list of like...
...things I should
have understood for a while.
Go figure it out. Yeah.
And like there are people on my team
who do understand it and would have better
...but like I actually don't
think I understand it well enough to know.
I s- I do have it kind
of in my this category of like- Yeah....
Like and there's a lot of things
that aren't like a huge paradigm shift.
Yeah.
But they're like pretty
big changes to how things run.
Yeah, totally.
And I expect like there are some of those
that will work.
Yeah, totally.
Um, I don't know if it's diffusion
or if it's another one.
Obviously, who knows what I
thought will be in the future, but at in
...the things where you see-...big areas
where a startup can win in the world in
...Anthropic is getting, you know,
making their models better year over year?
My general read is, like,
anything that benefits from the model
Yeah.
I think, like, on the one hand,
there's, like, a lot.
Y- you can always be like,
"Oh, yeah, the..." If you're doing a...
...startup, like,
all the AI labs are big companies. Yeah.
They'll be bigger than you
and they could do that thing. Yeah.
But also, like, we're all
working on this general system that
...Yeah....a lot of different uses,
and the, the plan is to, like, power...
...all the startups to do-
Right....all of the individual work.
So, yeah, I think, like,
anything that just kind of looks like,
...this almost works with
current models- Yeah....but requires,...
...like, a bunch of work
is a pretty promising direction.
Yeah.
Uh, I think maybe the thing
to watch out for is things where, like,
...a huge amount of work- Yeah....like,
to build up a scaffold, but the next...
...generation, they're,
you're not gonna need the whole scaffold
Yeah. Yeah.
That's, I mean,
maybe that's fine. I don't know.
Like, maybe you should build up-
Yeah....the business with the scaffold,
...then you don't have
to do any work later and you- Totally,
But l- I don't know
about the business end of it, but, like-
...does feel a little silly
to put- Yeah....to invest a ton in that.
Yeah, totally. What
about on the flip side?
Like, are there things in your training,
uh, stack where you're like, "Man, if
...was a company that solved X problem,
I would totally buy their product"?
Yeah. There's, like, a ton.
Yeah.
I do think that, like,
probably most of these, like, the way I
...structure it would be, like,
almost, like, making something but then
...with the com- Yeah....like
offering a service to companies for free.
Totally.
Particularly for, like,
companies that are scaling really fast.
You're almost always limited on,
like, how many people you can have.
So if you can, like- Ah, yeah.
Even if you could hire
people to do it yourself, after being able
...else- Yeah....to do it,
where, like, they're managing it and, you
...the people and, like,
deal with the organizational side, could
I mean, there's huge amount of stuff.
One that jumps to mind,
we talked about, like, chips that do math
Like, it would be lovely
if there was some startup that,...
...like, you could just say,
like, "Here are my chips.
Confirm they're all perfect." Mm.
"And if they're not, let me...
...know exactly what went wrong on,
like, what fraction of them,"...
...and, like, I,
I can tell you the math is wrong. Yeah.
But I couldn't really tell...
I don't really know enough
details of chips to be like, "This chip
...because this particular, like,
low-level component-" Right. "...was,
...wired wrong," or, like- Right,
totally....got hit by a gamma ray.
I, I don't, I don't know what causes it.
Yeah.
You could always go,
like, bunch, a bunch deeper.
I mean, the only thing I'd maybe just
push startups on is thinking a little bit
...like, uh, this is maybe less technical,
but just, like, what happens once we get
...and, like, how to make sure that,
like, goes well for the world or
Like my- Yeah....my expectation is, like,
if you actually...
...automate almost everything
a person can do, the amount of...
...economic growth there is just,
like, truly enormous.
And- Totally....
I would think a little more about,
like, how do you...
...make this, like,
help the world versus not?
I don't know.
I think there's gonna be,
like, plenty of economic success or...
...something a- as-
Yeah....a result of it anyway.
Yeah, absolutely. Yeah.
Um, last question I
wanna ask you is around if you, if we
...winding back to where we started,
like, 10 years ago.
Uh, you're a student.
You're pivoting into AI from
kind of economics work you were thinking
Um, and you know, all sorts of things
you probably did in those early days had
...of compounding return for you
as you developed into the role you have
Like, what advice would
you give to students as they think about,
...workforce, especially today, um,
learning skills that are gonna be useful
...getting themselves jobs like
the one you have right now 10 years later?
It's hard because I
think the timing is very different.
Like, I just think we're like...we've made, we've made a lot of progress.
So, like, what- Yeah....
I would do 10 years ago
is different from what I would- Sure,...
Totally.
But I think certainly if
I went back 10 years ago, I would be, on
It's, like- Yeah....the most important thing.
And- Yeah....particularly
focus on engineering, which I think felt
...Yeah....wouldn't have seemed obvious
to me at the time that, like, the...
...important thing was
these engineering skills and not the,
...and theoretical understanding of,
like, you know, uh, SVMs.
Yeah, totally.
Like, all the kind
of standard ML literature.
Um, I think today,
I would probably focus a bunch on the,
...engineering and on the, like,
figuring out what to do with AGI as
...of the two, like,
main things that feel top of mind for me.
Let's call it there.
Thanks so much, Nick. Appreciate it.
Cool.