Every three months, things have just
kept getting progressively better, and now...
...we're at this point where we're
talking about full-on vertical AI agents that...
...are going to replace entire teams
and functions and enterprises.
That progression is
still mind-blowing to me.
A lot of the foundation
models are kind of coming head-to-head.
There used to be only one
player in town with OpenAI, but we've...
...been seeing in the
last batch this has been changing.
Thank God.
I was like, competition is, you know,
the soil for a very fertile marketplace...
...ecosystem, uh, for which consumers
will have choice, and, uh,...
...founders have a shot,
and that's the world I want to live in.
Welcome to another episode of
The Light Cone. I'm Garry.
This is Jared, Harj, and Diana.
And collectively, we funded hundreds
of billions of dollars worth of...
...startups right when they were just one
or two people starting out.
And today, Jared is a man on fire,
and he's going to talk about vertical AI.
Yes, I am.
I am fired up about this
because I think people, especially...
...startup founders, especially young
ones, are not fully appreciating...
...just how big vertical
AI agents are going to be.
It's not a new idea.
Some people are talking about vertical AI agents,
we funded a bunch of them, but I...
...think the world has not caught on
to just how big it's going to get.
And so I'm going to make the case
for why I think there are going to be...
...$300 billion-plus companies
started just in this one category.
Nice.
I'm going to do it by analogy with SaaS,
and I think in a, in a similar fashion,...
...people don't understand just how big
SaaS is because most startup founders,...
...especially young ones, tend to see the
startup industry through the lens of the...
...products that they use as a consumer,
and as a consumer, you don't tend to...
...use that many SaaS tools
because they're mostly built for companies.
And so I think a lot of people have
missed the basic point that if you just look...
...at what Silicon Valley has been funding
for the most, for like, for the last...
...20 years, like, we've mostly
been producing SaaS companies, guys.
Like, that's literally been like most of
what has been coming out of Silicon Valley.
It's over 40% of all venture capital
dollars in that time period went to...
...SaaS companies, and we produced over
300 SaaS unicorns in that 20-year...
...time period, which is way
more than every other category.
Software's pretty awesome.
Yeah.
Software is pretty awesome.
I was thinking back to the history of
this because we, we always like to talk about...
...the, sort of how the, how
the history of technology informs the future.
And, um, the, the real
catalyst for, for this SaaS boom...
...was, uh,
do you guys remember XMLHTTPrequest?
Oh my God.
Like, I- I'd argue that that was
quite literally the catalyst for the SaaS boom.
Like, uh, AJAX?
AJAX, yeah.
In 2004, browsers added this JavaScript
function XMLHTTPrequest, which was the missing...
...piece that enabled you to build a
rich internet application in a web browser.
So, for the first time you
could make things in websites that...
...looked like desktop applications,
and then that created Google...
...Maps and Gmail and set up this whole,
like, SaaS boom.
Essentially, the, the key technology
unlock was that software moved from...
...being a thing that you got on a CD-ROM
and installed on your desktop to...
...being something that you use through
a website and on your phone.
Yeah.
Paul Graham actually, uh, shares in that lineage
in that he was one of the first...
...people to realize that he could take the
HTTP request and then actually hook it up...
...to a Unix prompt, and you didn't
actually have to, you know, have a separate-...
...Yeah. ... computer program- Yeah. ...
that would change a website.
So, ViaWeb was a, uh, online store, kind
of like Shopify, but way back in the day.
Yeah, it was basically like the
first SaaS app ever. Like, like- Right.
PG actually invented SaaS in like 1995.
It's just that those first SaaS
apps kind of sucked because they...
...didn't have XMLHTTPrequest,
and so every time you would like...
...click a button,
it would have to reload the whole page.
And so it's just a shitty experience,
and so it didn't really...
...catch on until 2005
when X- XMLHTTPrequest widespread.
Anyway, I, I see this LLM
thing as like actually very similar.
Um, it's like it's a new
computing paradigm that makes it possible...
...to just like do
something fundamentally different.
And in 2005, when cloud and mobile finally
took off, there is this sort of like...
...big open question of like,
okay, well, this new technology exists.
What should you do with it?
Where is the value going to accrue?
Where are the good
opportunities for startups?
I was going through the list of
like all the billion-dollar companies who were...
...created, and I kind of had this
realization that you could kind of bucket...
...the different paths
that people took into like three buckets.
Um, there's, there's a first bucket that
people started with, which was like I would...
...call them obviously good ideas
that could be mass consumer products.
Um, so that's like docs,
photos, email, calendar, chat, all...
...these things that like we used
to do on our desktop, but that...
...obviously could be moved to the browser
and to mobile.
And the interesting thing
is zero startups won in those categories.
100% of the value flowed to incumbents,
right?
Like Google, Facebook, Amazon, they
own all, all those businesses.
Folks forget that, like,
Google Docs wasn't the only company...
...that tried to
bring Microsoft Office online.
There were like 30 companies
that tried to bring...
...Microsoft Office online,
but they all lost.
Google won.
Then there was like a second category,
which was like mass consumer...
...ideas that were not obvious
that nobody predicted.
Um, that's like Uber,
Instacart, DoorDash, Coinbase, the- Airbnb.
New marketplaces.
Those ones, those ones came out
of left field like the, the dot-dot-dot...
...between XMLHTTPrequest
and Airbnb is like very not obvious.
Yeah.
And so the incumbents
didn't even try competing in...
...those spaces
until it was like too late.
And so startups were able to win there.
And then there's a third category,
which is all the B2B...
...SaaS companies,
and that's like 300 of them.
And so like mo- Like by, by,
by number of logos, way more billion-dollar...
...companies were created in
that third category than the first two.
I think one reason why
that happened is like...
...there is no......
like Microsoft of SaaS.
Like, there is no company
that somehow does, like, SaaS...
...for, like,
every vertical and every product.
Like, for structural reasons, it seems
to be the case that, like, they're...
...all different companies
and that's why there's so many of them.
I think Salesforce is probably,
like, the first true SaaS company.
Mm-hmm.
Um, and I, I remember Marc Benioff coming
to speak at YC and he tells a story.
It's just very early on.
People just didn't believe
you could build sophisticated enterprise...
...applications, like, over the
cloud or via SaaS. Yeah.
It was just so, um ... There
was just, like, a perception issue, right?
It was like, no, like you don't, you
buy, like, your box software and that's, like,...
...the real software that you run your-
This is the way we always do it.
It was, it was quite contrarian
'cause the early web apps sucked.
Yup.
They were, like, via web, where you had to
be a visionary like PG and understand- ... that...
...the browser was going to keep getting
better and that eventually it'd be good.
Which feels like quite
reminiscent of today, right?
Yeah.
Where it's like the, yeah, the same thing.
Like, oh, no.
Like, you won't be able
to build, like, sophisticated enterprise applications...
...that use these LLM or AI tools
because they hallucinate or they're...
...not perfect or they,
um, they're kind of like just toys.
But yeah, that's like the
early SaaS story exactly the same.
And so when I think about the
parallels with LLMs, I could easily imagine...
...this same thing happening, which is
that there's a bunch of categories...
...that are like mass consumer
applications that are obviously huge opportunities,...
...but probably the
incumbents will win all of those.
So, that's something like a pur- like
a general purpose AI voice assistant that you,...
...you know, you can ask it to do
anything and it'll, like, go do that thing.
That's an obvious thing that should exist,
but like, all the big...
...players are going to be
competing to be that thing, right?
Wow, Apple's a little slow on that one.
Why is Siri so stupid still?
What year is it? It makes no sense.
I mean, it's interesting.
Like, a count to that is, like, the
very obvious thing is search and maybe Google...
...will still win, um, on search, but
Perplexity is definitely give them a- Give...
...them a run for their money.
... huge run for their money, right?
Totally.
Yeah, this is the classic innovator's
dilemma at the end of the day.
I mean, you could argue, going back
to what you said about Uber or Airbnb,...
...these were actually really
risky things from a regulatory standpoint.
Yeah.
So, if you're Google and you
have basically a guaranteed, you know, giant,...
...uh, pot of gold that, you know,
sort of comes to you every single month,...
...like, why would you endanger that pot
of gold to sort of pursue these...
...things that, uh, might be scary
or might ruin the pot of gold?
I think that's a, I think that's,
like, probably the primary reason why the incumbents...
...didn't end up building those products
and didn't even clone them, even after...
...they got big and it was obvious that,
that they were going to work.
Google never launched an U- an Uber clone.
They never launched an Airbnb clone.
Um, I was listening to this, uh, talk by
Travis and one of the things that he said that...
...really stuck with me is that in the,
in the first years of Uber, he was very...
...scared that he was going to personally
go to prison for like, a long time.
Like, he was actually
personally risking going...
...to prison in order to build
that company.
And so yeah, no highly paid
Google exec was going to do that.
What do you think about, um, why
the incumbents didn't go into B2B SaaS?
Is it part of the reason is
that a lot of the use cases are very ...
There's a very wide distribution?
I ... It's a great question.
I love to hear what you guys think.
My take is that it's just too hard
to do that many things as a company.
Like, each B2B SaaS company really
requires, like, the people who are...
...running the product and the business
to be extremely deep in one domain...
...and care very deeply
about a lot of really obscure issues.
You know, like, take,
like, Gusto for example.
Like, why didn't Google
build a Gusto competitor?
Well, there's no one at Google who
really understands payroll and has the patience...
...to, like, deal with all the nuances
of all these, like, stupid payroll regulations...
...and like, it's just like,
like, it's just not worth it for them.
It's easier for them to just focus on,
like, a few really huge categories.
In the B2B SaaS world, it's, it's
sort of about the unbundling, bundling of software...
...argument that comes up a lot as well, I
think, and why didn't, why did all these vertical...
...B2B SaaS products evolve versus just,
like, Oracle or SAP or, um- NetSuite.
Yeah, NetSuite,
just owning, like, everything.
Um, and I think it might be als- ...
There's another thing that's attributable to
the shift to, like, SaaS and...
...the internet is in the old ways
of selling software, again, like, you had...
...this box software that was really,
like, expensive to install and you...
...had, like, a whole ecosystem around it,
and anytime you wanted something...
...custom, like,
the integrators would just say, "Oh, no.
Like, we can, like, just build you
a custom, like, payroll feature or something...
...like that." And then Salesforce comes
along with, like, a SaaS solution and...
...it just seems like it could never be
as powerful or sophisticated as,...
...like, the expensive
enterprise installation you just paid for.
But they proved that it totally
was the case, and I think that...
...just, like, opened the gates
for all of these, like, vertical...
...SaaS solutions to emerge
doing exactly what you're saying.
I think the other problem is that
with a lot of this enterprise software, if...
...you're a user of Oracle and a NetSuite,
because they're, they have to...
...cover so much ground, the
user experience is actually pretty bad.
They're trying to be jack of all trades,
but master of none.
Yeah.
So, it ends up being a bit
of a kitchen sink type of experience.
And this is where if you go and
build that B2B SaaS vertical company, you could do...
...literally a 10 X better experience
and more delightful because there's this stark...
...difference between consumer products
and enterprise user experience.
Yeah.
Well, there's only, uh, what?
Three price points in software.
It's, uh- ... $5 per seat,
$500 per seat, or $5,000 per seat.
And, uh, that maps directly
to consumer SMB or enterprise sales.
And then I think time immemorial has
taught us that in the past, and this...
...is less and less true, uh,
with new software thankfully, but enterprise...
...is terrible software
because it's not the user buying it.
You know, some high up mucky-de-muck inside
a Fortune 1000 is the person who's getting...
...wined and dined for this, you
know, mega seven-figure contract and, you know,...
...they're-... going to choose something that
maybe isn't that good actually for the...
...end user, the person who has
to actually use the software day-to-day.
And, um, I'm sort of curious to
see how this changes with LLMs actually.
I mean, to date, one of the more
salient things that we've seen for both SMB...
...and enterprise software companies is
that, or all software companies, all...
...startups, period, is like, you know,
there's a sense that as revenue...
...scales, the number of
people you have to hire scales with it.
And so, when you look at unicorns,
uh, even in today's YC portfolio, uh, it's...
...quite routine to see a company that
reached 100 or $200 million a year in...
...revenue, but they have like 500,
1,000, 2,000 employees already.
And I'm just gonna be very curious,
like, uh, even the advice that I'm...
...starting to give companies that are,
you know, a month or two out of...
...the batch, uh, it's, uh, it's
feeling a little bit different than...
...the kind of advice I would
give last year or two years ago.
In the past you might say, you
know, "Let me find the absolute smartest...
...person, uh, in all of these
other parts of the org, like customer...
...success, or sales,
or different things like that.
And, uh, I want to find someone who I've
worked with, who is, I know is great, and...
...then I'm going to go sit on their,
you know, uh, uh, on their doorstep until they...
...quit their jobs and come work for me."
"And I want them to be someone who can,...
...you know, build a team for me, hire
a lot of people." That might still be true,...
...but I'm starting to sense that,
uh, the meta shifting a little bit.
Like, you actually might want to
hire more really good software engineers who...
...understand large language models, uh,
who can actually automate the specific...
...things that you need
that are the bottlenecks to your growth.
And so it might result in, you know,
a very subtle but, you know, significant change in...
...the way startups grow their businesses,
sort of post-product market fit.
It means that I'm going to
build LLM systems that bring down my...
...cost, that cause me
not to have to hire 1,000 people.
I think we're right at the beginning of
that revolution right now.
I mean, we talked about
this in a previous episode.
We talked about there will
be a future unicorn company that's only...
...run, if we take it to the limit,
with only 10 employees.
That's completely plausible.
And they're writing the evils
and the prompts.
That's it.
I think what you're saying is like a trend
that was already underway pre-LLMs.
Like, I remember when I was running
Triplebyte, for example, we needed to, like, build...
...marketing or cust- like user acquisition
basically, um, and especially after we raised...
...our series B, the, like, traditional way you
were supposed to do that is to, like,...
...hire a marketing executive and build out,
like, a marketing team and, um, and just,...
...like, basically spin up this machine
to do, like, sales and marketing.
But I'd actually met, like, a
YC founder, um, Mike, who was...
His company was basically building,
like, a smart frying pan.
Sounds, like, bizarre, but, like, he
was a MIT engineer. I remember.
Yeah, you remember this?
Um, he's an MIT engineer, and to
sell the smart frying pan- Awesome. ... he...
...had to get really, really
good at understanding, like, paid advertising...
...and, um, uh, Google Ads,
and just a whole bunch of stuff.
And so he, he'd taken this
engineer's mindset approach to it, and I...
...remember just talking to him about it
and realizing this would be so...
...much better to have an MIT
engineer working on, like, our marketing...
...efforts than any of the
marketing candidates I've spoken to.
And he was able to,
like, scale us up to, like...
I mean we were spending, like,
at one point, like, a million dollars...
...a month on just marketing and various,
like, campaigns.
And, and Triplebyte had great marketing.
Yeah.
Like, I remember, like, the Caltrain- Yeah.
... station takeover that you did, all the,...
...like, out of home stuff that you did,
it was, like, really high quality stuff.
It stuck with the...
You could tell that it was not
being done by some, like- Yeah. ...
VP of marketing person.
And, th- um, and that was all Mike.
And, like, the comment I would
often get when people would ask me...
...around that time, like, "How big
is Triplebyte?" And we were like 50...
...people, and I would be able
to be- It felt so much better.
Yeah, yeah.
We'd be like, "Oh, there's like
hundreds of people." I was like,...
..."No, it's all because if you
put a really smart engineer on...
...some of these, like,
tasks, they just find ways to make...
They find leverage." And now,
like, LLMs can go even way beyond,...
...like, the leverage
you had with just pure software.
Okay, so here's my pitch
for 300 vertical AI agent unicorns.
Literally every company that is a SaaS
unicorn you could imagine, there is a vertical...
...AI unicorn equivalent in, like, some new
universe. 'Cause like most of these SaaS...
...unicorns, beforehand, there were some,
like, box software company that was...
...making the same thing that got disrupted
by a SaaS company, and you could...
...easily imagine the same thing happening
again, where now basically every S-...
...every SaaS company builds some software
that some group of people use.
The vertical AI equivalent
is just going to be the...
...software plus
the people in one product.
One thing might be just enterprises
in general right now are a little...
...unsure about what exactly they,
like what agents they need.
And one approach I've seen from
especially more experienced founders like, um,...
...Brett Taylor, the CTO of
Facebook, started this company, Sierra.
I don't know all the details, but as
far as I can tell, it's essentially more, like,...
...broadly about letting enterprises, like, deploy
these AI agents and spinning them...
...up, like, custom for the enterprise versus
like, "Oh, hey, we have, like, this...
...specific agent to do this." It's something
I've seen from one of my companies...
...called, um, uh, Vectorshift that
we funded about a year ago.
They're two really smart, like, Harvard
computer scientists, and it's a, they're...
What they found is that they're trying
to build a platform to make it easy...
...for enterprises to build their own,
like, use, like, no code or SDKs...
...to build their own,
like, um, internal LLM powered agents.
But, like,
enterprises often don't know exactly...
...what they want to use these things for.
And so, bringing it back, I wonder if,
like, in, like, the box software world,...
...you started off with just, like, a
few vendors who just basically were trying...
...to convince people to use software at
all- Yeah. ... and it was just like,...
...it does everything, um, and then
it gets more sophisticated and higher...
...resolution and you get lots of,
like, vertical SaaS players.
We go through that same period with LLMs
where the early winners might just be these, like,...
...general purpose, "Hey, like, we, like, make it
easy for you to do LLM stuff," and then...
...it...... the vertical agents will come in
over time, or do you think there's...
...reasons it's different now and the vertical
agents will take off on day one?
Yeah, that's interesting,
'cause if you think about the...
...history of SaaS,
the consumer things worked first.
Like, 2005 to 2010 was mostly consumer
applications like email and chat and maps.
And people got, y- people, uh, as
individuals, got used to using these tools...
...themselves, and I think that made it
easier to sell SaaS tools to companies...
...because, you know, the same
people are both employees and consumers.
Yeah.
I, I think the answer might just be,
like, this is, this is all just a continuation...
...of software and just there's no
reason it has to reset back.
Like, LLMs don't have to reset back
to a few general purpose, like, enterprise...
...LLM platforms doing everything, because
enterprises have already been trained...
...on, like, the value of
point solutions and vertical solutions.
Um, and, like, the user experience
is not going to be that different.
These things will
just be a lot more powerful.
And so if enterprises have already
built the muscle of believing that, like,...
...startups or vertical solutions can
be better than, like, legacy broad...
...platforms, they are probably
going to be willing to take a bet on a...
...startup promising a very
good vertical AI agent solution today.
And I feel like we're all seeing
that in the batch now, where some of...
...our companies are getting
faster traction in enterprises for...
...these vertical AI agents than,
like, we've ever seen before.
I think we're just early in the game,
right?
Like, all software sort of starts
quite vertical, and then as the...
...industries actually get much
more developed, um, then...
I mean,
I just answered my earlier question.
It's like, you know, why does a
company end up having a thousand employees?
It's actually that, uh, you know, early,
early in the game everyone's making these...
...specific point solutions, and then at
some point you've got to go horizontal.
Like, you're already doing this crazy spend
on sales and marketing, and then the...
...only way you can actually continue to grow
once you sort of get 100% or, you...
...know, some large majority of the market,
is you actually have to do, like,...
...not just a point solution,
but things that sort of work together.
Maybe the other point of why the bull
case for vertical AI agents could be even...
...bigger than SaaS is that SaaS, you still
needed a operations team or set of people...
...to operate the software in
order to get all the workflows to be done.
I don't know, approval workflows or
you have to input the data.
The argument here is that you will
get not only replacing all that set of...
...SaaS software, so that would
be, like, one-to-one mapping, but it's...
...also going to eat all of
the, a lot of the payroll. Totally.
Because you look a lot
of the spend for companies, big...
...chunk is still a payroll,
and software's tiny.
Exactly. They spend way more on
employees than they do on software.
So it'll be these smaller companies that
are way more efficient, that need way...
...less humans to do random data entry
or approvals or click the software.
I agree.
I think it's very possible that
the vertical equivalents will be 10...
...times as large as the
SaaS company that they are disrupting.
Yeah.
I mean there's, there's two case.
It could be that the vertical
point solution could be just big enough...
...and you don't need to
do that bra- breadth thing, right?
It, that could be another scenario.
Should we give some examples?
I feel like we've all been-
Now's a good time to talk about some. ...
working with so many vertical AI
agent companies, we've got, like, news...
...from the front- Yeah.
... of like- ... how it's actually going.
Well, your former, uh, head of
product, Aaron Cannon, is working on a...
...YC company called Outset that
I worked with and, uh, basically...
...they're taking LLMs,
uh, to the surveys and Qualtrics space.
So Qualtrics is almost
certainly not really going to build the...
...best of breed, uh,
large language model with reasoning.
And then the funny thing about surveys is,
you know, who's it actually for?
It's for people who run products, for marketing
teams, it's for people who are trying to...
...make sense of, like, what do our
customers actually want, and what are surveys?
Like, guess what? That's language.
So, um, and then I feel like these
types of businesses, um, actually have to thread...
...this needle, um, because enterprise and SMB
software often is sold based on a particular...
...person who is the key decision-maker, and, um,
you have to go high enough in the...
...organization so that the people you're
selling to are not afraid that their...
...whole, their job and or their whole
team's job is going to go away.
Yeah.
Totally.
That's kind of the move that I seen
that a lot of companies that sell need...
...to do, because if you're going to
go and sell to the team that's going...
...to get replaced by AI- Oh yeah,
they're gonna sabotage it, man.
Yep. ... it just does not work.
Yeah.
So I think this is a interesting way that
a lot of these are top down and you...
...have to go through, at some point even
get the CEO to sign off on it.
Yeah.
A company I'm working with, uh, Momentic,
that's sort of a, essentially an AI...
...agent, but for at least where
they're starting is, like, QA testing.
Um, they're actually getting really great
traction right now, and it's interesting because...
...do you remember a decade ago,
um, YCombinator we worked with Rainforest QA.
Like, Rainforest was a QA as a
service company, and that they had this exact...
...tension of where they couldn't actually replace
your QA team, and so they needed...
...to build software that made the
QA team more, like, efficient, but really...
...that obviously meant trying to replace
as many of them as possible.
They couldn't replace the whole team, and so
they were always on this sort of, like,...
...tightrope between trying to sell the software
to, like, the head of engineering- ...
and said this will mean you'll need
less QA people, and great, but then you...
...also have to go sell that to the
QA team who don't want to be replaced.
And so I think that was always,
like, a friction for that...
...business for how it could,
like, scale and grow.
But now, like, Momentic with AI
can actually just replace the QA people.
So their pitch is not, oh, this, like,
makes your QA people faster, it's like, this just...
...means you don't need a QA team at all,
so they can just focus the sale onto, like,...
...engineering and engineering
doesn't need buy-in from QA at this point.
And you can also go in...
I mean, to start with, you can
go and sell to companies that don't even...
...have big QA teams at the moment,
they just use something like...
...Momentic and then it will just,
like, keep scaling with them.
Scaling and they'll just never build
a QA team- Yeah. ... ever.
Yeah.
Yes.
That is a real life case study of
what Diana was saying about why these vertical...
...AI agent companies can be 10 times
as big as the SaaS companies.
Yeah. I'm seeing this interesting
now, um, like in recruiting too.
I had this exact same issue with Oh. ...
Triplebyte- ... where to build the software,
um, to build software that makes it...
...easy to, like, screen and hire
software engineers you need buy-in from both...
...the engineering team that they're
joining, but also their recruiting team,...
...and effectively the software we were
building was trying to replace the...
...recruiters, but we couldn't
completely replace the recruiters.
But now within YC there's- Yeah,
and so the recruiters were always, like,...
...uh...... opposing- Yeah. ... opposing it
'cause it was a threat to them.
Yeah. Yeah.
So it was always, like, friction on like how,
um, on like how far you can get when...
...the customer you're trying to sell
to is worried about being replaced.
Um, but yeah.
I think now, it's still early days,
but now with AI you can...
...build things that do the whole stack,
like of recruiting.
We have a company we worked with last,
Patrick, Nico worked with them,...
...apriora, which is actually just doing
like the full like technical screen,...
...the full initial recruiter screen,
and getting great traction.
So I think as those things keep going,
like they won't have...
The, the same thing,
you won't have the friction of,...
...oh, I need to
convince recruiters to use this.
You'll probably just,
like, not build a recruiting...
...team in the same way that you used to.
I mean, other w- example
is even for dev tool companies,...
...they have to do a lot of,
uh, developer support.
And I work with this
company called Capilot.ai that basically built...
...one of the best chatbots that responds
to a lot of the, a lot...
...of the technical details, uh,
that are hard to answer.
And I think a lot of the
companies that started using them, they actually...
...ended up having DevRel teams that are
a lot smaller- Mm-hmm. ... because it...
...ingests a lot of, uh,
the developer documentations, even the YouTube...
...videos that c- dev tools put up,
and even a lot of the chat history.
So it just keeps getting
better and better, and is...
...like, gives really
good answers actually.
It's one, one of the best I've seen.
Yeah, I also worked with a
customer support, uh, like an AI...
...customer support
agent company called PowerHelp.
Mm-hmm.
Well, actually- Yeah. ...
we- w- we both did, um, last batch.
And I learned a couple
interesting things from PowerHelp.
Um, the first is customer sup-
like AI agents for customer support...
...was like the category that's
like famously crowded, where there's...
...like supposedly like,
you know, a hundred of them.
And if you go and you
google like AI customer support- Yeah.
... agent, you'll get like
a hundred results on Google.
Um, but what I learned
through working with PowerHelp...
...is, like,
it's actually kind of bullshit.
Like, like, almost all of those
companies are doing very simple, like,...
...zero-shot LLM prompting that can't
actually replace a real customer...
...support team that does a
lot of really complicated w- workflows.
It just kind of
makes for like a nice demo.
Like, to actually replace a customer
support team for like an at scale...
...company that has like a hundred
customer support reps that do lots of...
...complicated things every day, you
need like really complicated software...
...that does all the stuff
that like Jay Keller was talking about.
And there's on- there were only like three
or four...
...companies that were
even attempting to do that.
And cumulative they ha- cumulatively they
had like less than 1% market penetration.
And so the market
was just completely open.
I could also see
that being another case of, um,...
...hyper-specialization
or hyper-verticalization.
Yeah.
Like there's not going to be...
I mean, maybe eventually there could
be a single general-purpose customer support...
...agent- Yeah. ... software company, but
we're like in inning, you know, that,...
...that'll be like an eighth or
ninth inning kind of thing. Totally.
And we're literally in the first inning.
So, you know, instead, you know,
you're going to have companies like GigaML...
...that, you know, it's doing it
for Zepto doing 30,000 tickets, uh,...
...every single day and replacing a,
a team of a thousand people.
Yeah.
And, but it's very specific and it has,
you know, it's...
...not a general-purpose
demoware kind of thing.
Like it's 10,000 test cases and
a very detailed, uh, eval set that,...
...you know, is basically just
for Zepto and things like Zepto.
Yeah.
Uh, but if you are, you know,
any of the other marketplace companies,...
...you're probably gonna use it, 'cause
like that's a very well-defined kind...
...of marketplace that's,
you know, instant delivery marketplace.
I think this is the kind- Mm-hmm. ...
of dynamic that led there to be like...
...$300 billion SaaS companies rather than
like one like $10 trillion like...
...meta SaaS thing that provides
all the software for the world.
It's just like the customers just
require really heavily, like, tailored solutions...
...and it's hard to build one
that like works for every, everyone.
Exactly.
I mean, we already
gave three examples of customer...
...support, but they
are very different verticals.
Yeah.
It's like dev tool companies, very
different kind of support that you need,...
...and the training set to
marketplace is very different, right?
Yeah, I guess whether you have agents or real
human beings working for you, you end up with...
...the same problem, which is every company
bumps up against Coase's theory of the firm,...
...which says that- Mm-hmm. ... any given firm
will grow only so much to the point where...
...it, uh, becomes inefficient to be larger
than that, and then that's why there are...
...sort of, uh, networks and ecosystems
and, you know, a full-blown economy.
You know, like every firm will sort
of specialize to do what it is particularly...
...good at, and then the limits, the
outer limits of what those firms can...
...be, it's actually based on,
uh, m- your ability as a manager.
So yeah, that, that part a little
bit breaks my brain because, you know, when...
...we spend time with Parker Conrad at
Rippling, uh, one of his favorite points...
...is actually, well, you know, everyone's
very obsessed with, with, uh, the...
...fact that the rocks can talk and,
you know, maybe they can draw, but...
...the more interesting thing for him,
you know, running HRIT software...
...that, uh, you know,
he spends a lot of time thinking about HR.
Like actually the coolest thing about
LLMs is that the rocks can read.
Yeah.
And from his perspective, like, you know,
he's, he, I think he has 3,000 employees.
He still runs payroll for
all 3,000 employees through Rippling.
So I think he spends a
lot of time thinking about like, how...
...can one person extend their ability
as a manager?
And, uh,
I think we're gonna see a lot more there.
That would be in a, a reverse argument
that if we're at this moment where, uh, tools...
...for managers and CEOs are going to
get much more powerful, um, then- Oh, it...
...could- it could- it could increase the
scale of the firm that you can run.
Right.
And that's certainly
what Rippling is trying to do.
Yeah, this is sort of the war, right?
Mm-hmm.
Like he's- he's- he's attempting
to build this like suite of HR tools...
...where if he wins- Yeah. ...
he's gonna eat a whole bunch of billion...
...dollar SaaS companies in like one,
one giant company.
It's a very- Yeah.
... interesting point, Gary.
I think what made me think about this is
that with having all these AI...
...SaaS tools is gonna...... give the
ability to all these leaders and...
...all these orgs, who basically
open the aperture of the context...
...window, or how much information
they can- Oh, yeah. ... parse.
Mm-hmm.
Because there's a limit of how much, uh,
as humans...
...we can have meaningful relationship.
There's like the whole thing
with the Dunbar number- Oh, yeah.
It's about 300 people that you can- 150.
... 150, that...
...you can have a
meaningful relationship with.
But with AI, because all these
rocks now can read, I think we...
...will be able to extend
that Dunbar limit that we have.
Yeah, I think, uh,
Flo Crivello had this interesting...
...post on Twitter
that went viral around, um...
I think someone had made a voice chat,
like just weekend project as a CEO,...
...but it would call, uh, all
1,500- Right. ... of their employees.
Mm. Yeah.
And, uh, you know, it was, you
know, a very short call, like kind of...
...sounded like it was from the CEO,
just asking kind of personally.
I mean, it sort of reminds me of, um,
that scene in Her where it zooms out and, uh,...
...actually, you know, you're following the
experience of one person using the Her...
...OS, but actually, that Her OS
is actually speaking to 15, you know,...
...thousands or tens of thousands of people
all at- Oh, yeah. ... one time.
How- how many others? 8316.
Yeah, I mean, large language models
can talk and can have conversations.
And then to what extent can, uh,
you know, this power actually extend the...
...capability of one or a few people to,
uh, understand what's going on?
I, I, I heard about that use case.
It got, it definitely got me thinking
because I, as I understood it, the...
...product is something that you just,
it will call up all your employees and...
...then your employees can just like
ramble about what they've been doing and...
...it will just extract the meaning out
of it and give the CEO like ev-...
...like bullet point summary
of here's the most important stuff.
And there were a bunch of like SaaS
companies that attempt to do these sort of like...
...weekly pulse, pulses from employees
using like traditional SaaS software.
But like, that version
is literally 100 times better...
...than the pre-LLM version of this idea.
But I wonder with like that particular
tool, um, just like i- i- it's not...
It's going beyond just like reading
and summarizing.
Like this, this is the argument of like,
if writing is thinking then...
...like there's actually just a huge
amount of work that's involved in...
...the effort of figuring out
like who's an effective communicator...
...and like what are the
most important things to be like...
What, what are the key things
to be focused on as a company?
And I just wonder if that, uh, at
some point do the LLMs do like, they go...
...beyond just like summarizing and
reading and doing actual thinking, at...
...which point like who's
actually running the, the organization?
Yes.
Interesting thought.
I guess the other thing that's kind
of interesting about how Parker Conrad's thinking about...
...it is, um, I found out about this
recently off, uh, an interview with Matt McInnis, his...
...COO, that, uh, there are more than 100
founders who work at Rippling now, as sort...
...of specific people who run like
an entire SaaS vertical inside Rippling.
It's super cool the
way he's built the team.
Har- Harsh probably
knows a l- lot about it because...
...you've done a
bunch of interviews with him.
Um, yeah, I mean, it's definitely
very focused on, uh, recruiting founders and...
Uh, I mean, uh, Parker, uh,
like Rippling is essentially the, the case...
...against vertical, like,
or verticalization of software, right?
He's actively trying to, uh, horizontalize and
take over all of HR and IT software.
Yeah.
Like the whole thesis is
basically there's this underlying platform...
...that has like lots of value
and he wants to recruit founders...
...and teams
that build on top of that platform.
Like it's almost a little
bit more sort of like Amazon-esque-...
...Yeah. ...
where it's like shared infrastructure.
Um- Yeah, I think
every product that they've released,...
...I mean,
things like time tracking and whatnot.
I mean, basically they launch a
thing and it hits like multi-millions...
...of dollars in
ARR on day one of launching.
And that's exactly what
we were talking about earlier.
Like once you, once you have a vertical,
once you have a toehold, what you're saying...
...is, "Well, I have to spend
this money on sales and marketing anyway.
Can I, uh, you know,
basically get higher LTV and hold my...
...CAC constant?" And,
uh, that's sort of what...
If you, if you look at all the
top, uh, software companies today, it's like that's...
...what Oracle is, that's what
Microsoft is, that's what Salesforce is.
Rippling, knock on wood,
going to be the next.
But, um, it's,
it's an interesting alternative to,...
...uh, going from zero
to one totally on your own.
Do you guys want to talk about
some of the voice companies that we have?
I think that's like an interesting,
like, subcategory of...
...this, of this stuff
that's like really blowing up now.
I have a company that I work with
called Salient that basically does AI voice calling to...
...automate a lot of debt collection in
the auto lending space, which traditionally- So they...
...like call up people and are like,
"Hey, you owe $1,000 on your car." Yeah.
Which actually- "What's
up with that?" Actually, this...
...kind of job is one
of those butter passing job.
It kind of sucks because a lot of,
uh, these low wage workers work in...
...all these call centers
and it's like a terrible boring job.
So very high churn and giant
headcount to run these because there's...
...just so many accounts with these banks
that have to do that.
And this is a perfect task
that AI could automate.
And what Salient has done is, has been
able to actually get very, very accurate and...
...it has been going live with a
lot of big banks, which is super exciting.
And this was a company from last
year and demonstrating that, that part of it...
...that they were able to get in
because they sold through top down.
I guess the space feels like
it's moving very quickly and that we...
...have incredible companies
that are voice infra companies, like...
...Vapi, and then people
can sort of get started right away.
And retail also.
I mean, these are companies that
have reached pretty fast scale just because...
...it's one of the more exciting,
like mind-blowing things that you can get...
...up and running within,
I mean, literally the course of hours.
Um-And then some of the question that,
you know, remains unanswered,...
...and we hope they figure it out,
is how do you hold onto them?
Especially as you, uh, run into
things like the new OpenAI voice APIs.
Um, you know, do you go direct?
Like, you prob- it's probably way more
work to try to use the underlying...
...APIs off the bat, but
these, uh, platforms are clearly low-bar.
And then the question is
can you keep raising the ceiling...
...so that you can
hold onto customers forever?
Harj, you were making an
interesting point earlier about, like,...
...how the apps that people have
built on top of LMs has changed...
...from, like,
early 2023 when it started until now.
Yeah. Voice, which we were just talking
about, is a great example of this.
I think even if you went six months back,
it felt...
...like the voices
were not realistic enough yet.
The latency was too high.
Like, there was n- W- It felt like we
were probably a ways off having AI voice apps...
...that could meaningfully, like, replace,
like, humans calling people up.
And, like, here we are.
And yeah, we're just sort of zooming out,
thinking back to the...
...first YC batch
where LLM-powered apps first came in.
It was probably winter 2023,
so, you know, almost two years ago now.
And the apps were essentially just things
that spat out...
...some text,
and not even, like, perfect text.
The rocks could talk, that's about it.
Yeah, right?
Sort of more like copyediting,
marketing edit- Yeah. ... email edits.
It was just, uh, kind of more,
like, just, like, incremental.
Yeah. Like I re- I had a company...
I mean, the one that sticks in
my head is a company called Speedy Brand,...
...and all, what they did is make
it very easy for, like, a small business...
...to just generate a blog
and spit out content marketing.
Um, it was like a very obvious idea.
And it wasn't perfect, but it was
pretty cool at the time, and that's what...
We've talked about it a bunch on the show,
but that was like...
...the ChatGBT wrapper,
it turned out, around that time.
So hey, like, this is what
an LLM app looks like, it's...
...just a ChatGBT wrapper,
it does very basic...
Spits out some text.
Like, it's going to get crushed by OpenAI
in their next release. Like- And it did.
Yeah.
Well, I don- I don- I don't
know if- No, Speed- ... that one did,...
...but- but the- that- that first,
that first wave of LLM apps...
...mostly did get crushed
by the next wave of- Right. ...
GPTs, yeah.
But I- I feel like we've had
this sort of boiling of the frog effect,...
...where from our perspe- it's sort
of like every f- three months,...
...things have just
kept getting progressively better.
And now we're at this point where
we're talking about, like, full-on vertical AI...
...agents that are going to replace
entire teams and functions and enterprises.
Um, and just that progression is
still mind-blowing to me.
Like, we're two years in, which
is still relatively early, and the rate...
...of progress is just,
like, unlike anything we've seen before.
And I think what's interesting to see is,
we discussed this in the last episode,...
...is a lot of the foundation
models are kind of coming head-to-head.
There used to be only one player
in town with OpenAI- Mm-hmm. ... but...
...we've been seeing in
the last batch this has been changing.
Claude is a huge contender.
Thank God. 'Cause like competition is, you
know, the- the soil for a very...
...fertile marketplace ecosystem, uh, for
which consumers will have choice, and,...
...uh, founders have a shot,
and that's the world I want to live in.
So people are watching and thinking
about starting a startup or maybe...
...have already started,
and, uh, they're hearing all of this.
How do you know what
the right vertical is for you?
You got to find some boring,
repetitive admin work somewhere.
And that seems to be just, like, the common
thread across- Yes. ... all of this stuff, is...
...if you can find a boring, repetitive admin
task, um, there is likely going to be a...
...billion-dollar AI agent startup
if you keep digging deep enough into it.
But it sounds like you should
go after something that you directly...
...have some sort of experience
or relationship to.
That is a common, like, that
is definitely a common thread I've seen...
...in the companies that are,
that I'm seeing promise with.
And- and another one just
pops into my head, Sweet Spot.
I think I mentioned on this before, like,
they're basically building an AI agent to bid on...
...government contracts, and the way they found that
idea, and this is a year ago, was they...
...just had a friend whose full-time job was
to sit there on, like, a government website,...
...like, refreshing the page,
like, looking for new proposals to bid on.
And they- they were pivoting, and they
were like, "Oh, like, that seems like something...
...an LLM could do." Um, a company from
a recent batch which pivoted into a new...
...idea that's getting great traction,
like, they're basically building an AI...
...agent to do, um, processes
like medical billing for dental clinics.
And the way they found the idea was,
um, one of the founder's...
...mothers is a dentist, and so he
just decided to go to work with...
...her for a day and just sit there,
seeing what she did.
And he's like, "Oh,
like, all of that, like,...
...processing claims seems,
like, really boring.
Like, an LLM should totally be able
to do that." And he just started...
...writing software for,
like, his mother's dental clinic.
So I guess, I mean, in robotics,
the classic maxim is, uh, you...
...know, the robots that are going
to be profitable and that are...
...going to work are going to be,
um, dirty and dangerous jobs.
And in this case, for vertical
SaaS, look for boring- ... butter-passing jobs.
Yeah.
Well, with that,
we're out of time for today.
We'll catch you on the light...
...cone next time.